<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Nicerotis a pleasant novel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828705</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828705</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1868:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Nicerotis a pleasant novel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Bentley and S. Magnes, at the Post-house in Russel-street in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption and running titles read: The fragment of the history of Nicerotis.</note>
                  <note>Includes advertisement, p [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nicerotis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF Nicerotis, A Pleaſant NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> at the Poſt-houſe in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33136:2"/>
            <head>TO THE DUTCHESS OF <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have often obſerved the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of too obſtinately maintaining an Opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which has generally obtained, and in ſerious or weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Matters have carefully avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Rock upon which I have known ſome to have been loſt;
<pb facs="tcp:33136:3"/> but in our laſt Converſe, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject whereof was the Fineſs with which the Ladies and Gallants of this preſent Age manage their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which the Company then preſent unanimouſly agreed was advanced to a perfection, no former Age could parallel; hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncontrouledly aſſerted the contrary; and perhaps too poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and having given an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome Paſſages of above five hundred years ago, which you all would poſitively conclude to be a Fiction, till I ſatisfi'd you, that I met with the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in an antient Greek Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, which by the Injury of time, and the Ignorance of the
<pb facs="tcp:33136:3"/> Perſons, through whoſe hands it had paſſed, was very imperfect, as having neither beginning nor ending; and in ſome places not legible, and with many interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſome excellent Paſſages, yet contain'd enough to juſtifie my Aſſertion, and to convince the Hearers, that in that Age and Countrey, there were Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who lived much after our Mode, and that there is nothing new under the Sun. I thought I ſhould have had the general applauſe of that illuſtrious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, for having ſo well juſtified my ſelf; but inſtead thereof, am puniſht with their and your indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible Commands, to put what
<pb facs="tcp:33136:4"/> remains of that Piece; the ſhort account whereof was agreeably received by you, into a Language intelligible to perſons more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in affairs of that nature, than acquainted with the Tongue in which before now it was only extant. My Style, I know, is very unfit for the Subject, and my time deſigned for a far different Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; but rather than diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige ſo many, and ſo fair Friends, I have put a Force upon my ſelf, and ſequeſtered ſome few hours for this her View, but freely profeſs to you, it is a Piece very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in the Matter, by the Misfortune and Injury of many Ages, but more by the rudeneſs
<pb facs="tcp:33136:4"/> of the Tranſlators Style, who in the Judgment of the Learned, will be cenſur'd for having done the elegant Author much wrong; but in regard his Name is not known, and ſo none can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for him, I cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to reparation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with more confidence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to you, as it is with all its Defects.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:33136:5"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome <hi>Novels</hi> and <hi>Plays</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>NOVELS.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>ZElinda,</hi> a fam'd Romance.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Happy Slave,</hi> in three Parts.</item>
               <item>3 Count <hi>Brion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 Count <hi>Gabales.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Hatige,</hi> or the Amours of the King of <hi>Tamaran.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 Mad. <hi>Lavalier</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 <hi>Madam</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 Mad. <hi>Colonna</hi>'s Memoirs.</item>
               <item>9 Queen of <hi>Majork,</hi> two Parts.</item>
               <item>10 Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 Heroine Muſquetier.</item>
               <item>12 Princeſs of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 Obliging Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>14 Fatal Prudence.</item>
               <item>15 Princeſs of <hi>Fez.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16 Diſorders of Love.</item>
               <item>17 Triumph of Love.</item>
               <item>18 Victorious Lovers.</item>
               <item>19 <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaida.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20 <hi>Nicoſtratis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21 Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>22 <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> or, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of his Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>23 Amorous Abbeſs.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>Homais</hi> Queen of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>25 Pilgrim, in two Parts.</item>
               <item>26 <hi>Merovius,</hi> Prince of the Blood-Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>27 Life of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>28 Extravagant Poet.</item>
               <item>29 <hi>Memoires Gallant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>30 Inſtruction for a young Nobleman.</item>
               <item>31 Grand <hi>Alconder.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>32 Chaſt <hi>Seraglion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the Preſs.</head>
               <item>33 <hi>Adellaid,</hi> a fam'd Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</item>
               <item>34 The Amours of <hi>Catu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>35 The Illuſtrious <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noueſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33136:5"/>
            <head>THE FRAGMENT OF THE HISTORY OF Nicerotis.</head>
            <div n="1-44" type="pages">
               <p>AH unfortunate <hi>Nicerotis!</hi> To what infelicities art thou deſtin'd? No ſooner does the world take notice of thy blooming Beauties, but thou art hurri'd away into a Deſart; no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooner become the Adoration of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Court upon Earth, but thou art ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd from it, and baniſh'd to an obſcure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſland, as if Youth and Beauty were a Crime: Thou muſt ſuffer the puniſhment of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors, for pleaſing the ſweeteſt and moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iging Monarch that ſits upon a Throne.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33136:6"/> Too late I perceive the difference between a Lover and a Huſband. Where are the Vows, my dear <hi>Nicias,</hi> ſo often made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could prevail with me, to give him my heart? How often did he, with the moſt ſolemn Oaths proteſt, his whole Life ſhould be employ'd to pleaſe me: That he never would entertain ſo much as a Thought, that ſhould be diſagreeable to mine? That my Inclinations ſhould govern his with a Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy? But he is now on a ſudden grown po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and imperious, as the Guardian Eunuch of the Palace, and inflexible as a peeviſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Father. While <hi>Nicerotis</hi> thus paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately bewail'd her condition, <hi>Phylaenis</hi> who was employ'd in her Cabinet, and overheard ſome part of her Lamentation, coming from thence, and making uſe of the Confidence that was between them, thus interrupted her: Madam, What means this weakneſs in a Perſon of your Quality? It ill becomes one of your Underſtanding and Spirit, to grieve at the Traverſes of Fortune: Perſons like you, either foreſee their Adverſities at a diſtance, and then conſult how to avoid or oppoſe them, or when they are ſurpriz'd, bear them with courage. Before you ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted your ſelf to the Dominion of a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, you ſhould have believed thoſe that told you they are all Tyrants, whoſe Will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33136:6"/> is their Law, and Intereſt their only affection; when their firſt Heats are cool'd, their Paſſion becomes in the beſt of them Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in ſome indifferency, but in the moſt, an Averſion. If a poor Soul fall into the hands of one of them, if he be a Fool, ſhe is preſently perſecuted with a thouſand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, groundleſs Quarrels, Suſpitions, and Jealouſies without cauſe, croſs Humors, peeviſh, and always unſeaſonable Wars: But of the two, a wiſe man is the greater E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; ſo many Precepts and Cautions, ſuch Pretenſions and Circumſpection, a Woman had better forſwear the World, and be cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd up, then be bound to the Rules of his Order. Your Satyr againſt Marriage is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as unſeaſonable, reply'd <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> as my Complaints againſt Fortune; but I muſt confeſs, you have a little rais'd my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and made me ſenſible, 'tis fitter to think of ſome way to prevent, if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, this ſudden Retreat, than vainly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail it; the time is very ſhort, and if your Invention be as happy in this Inſtant, as I have ſometime found it, you ſhall ever be my Tutelar Angel. <hi>Phylaenis,</hi> who was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Experience, as well as great preſence of mind in ſuch Affairs, had formed in her thoughts an Expedient, which ſo pleas'd her own Fancy, that with great aſſurance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33136:7"/> and Gaity in her Countenance, ſhe cry'd out, Madam, be no more afflicted; if you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve not to be wanting, to your ſelf, I dare promiſe to ſtop your Journey for ſome months, if you will conſent to — At this word, <hi>Niceas</hi> entred the Room, and <hi>Phylaenis</hi> in ſome confuſion, for fear ſhe had been overheard by her Lord, withdrew, to leave it to her Lady, to receive the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of his Reſentments; but he coming in great haſt, as being intent upon the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of a Deſign, which he knew admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no delay, where the leaſt omiſſion might prove an unavoidable ruine, was ſo taken up with it, that if he overheard any of their Words, he yet knew not that he did: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſays he, I have been to perform thoſe neceſſary Civilities for you, to thoſe of your Friends and Relations, who are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in you, and I have ſatisfi'd them, that it is indiſpenſibly requiſite for preſerving my Life and Honour, that we proceed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately on our Journey: The Galley lies ready upon her Oars in a week without the Harbour, and I am come to conduct you thither; there is no time to be loſt, call your Woman, and let us be going, we ſhall have better leiſure to diſcourſe the motives of this ſo ſudden reſolution in our Voyage, and taking her by the hand, he call'd out to <hi>Phylaenis</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33136:7"/> her Lady, and ſaid he had given order to the Steward, to ſend all their Neceſſaries by another way, to meet them at the Ship ſide. The Surprize was moſt aſtoniſhing to <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> but giving her hand to her Lord, <hi>Nicias,</hi> ſays ſhe, you are all the World to me, and where-ever I go with you, that place will be more pleaſing to me, than all the Delights and Glories of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I cannot only be content but happy with you in a Deſart: Let us go then; where you pleaſe, and though I have been inſtructed, the great Reſpects that ought to be paid to Relations, Familiars, and Superiours upon ſuch occaſions, and that the neglect of them, does always, if not deſtroy, at leaſt diminiſh the eſteem that perſons of Quality ought to deſire to live in, in the World; I have now learnt, that an abſolute conformity to the Government of a Huſband is the greateſt Duty, as well as Felicity of a Wife. Madam, reply'd <hi>Nicias,</hi> as we go, I will ſatisfie all your Scruples; and to convince you of the neceſſity of this abrupt departure, that you will confeſs, I only wanted time to let you know the Reaſons of it beforehand, to have made it your Reſolution before it was mine. By this time they were at the Chariot, and being entred, were ſoon at the Water-ſide, having only to paſs a Back-way by the Walls
<pb facs="tcp:33136:8"/> of the Palace-Gardens; ſo that unobſerv'd they went aboard the Gally that attended them, and immediately ſetting forward with a gentle ſtroak of their Oars, they made no great haſt, that a ſmall Sloop, which was to bring their Servants and Neceſſaries, juſt with the fall of Night, might overtake them. <hi>Nicerotis</hi> follow'd by her Woman, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted into the State-room of the Gally by the Captain, who leaving her there, went out to wait on <hi>Nicias,</hi> who was got upon the Poop, to obſerve the pleaſant Shores on both ſides the <hi>Helleſpont;</hi> and to take notice of Landmarks, by which the Pilots govern their Courſe in paſſing thoſe Straits. The Day being calm, and the motion of the Veſſel ſteady and ſlow, the Lady and her Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did not yet perceive that Diſcompoſure creeping on them, which being at Sea, brings upon moſt Conſtitutions not accuſtomed to it, ſo that they were not interrupted by it, to entertain themſelves with the Diſcourſe of their preſent Condition; and <hi>Phylaenis</hi> firſt breaking ſilence, Madam, ſaid ſhe, it is no time to ſhew your Ladiſhip, the means I had found out to have retarded this Voyage, which I had juſt then modell'd, and was going to propoſe to you when my Lord came upon us, and I fear, overheard ſome part of a Converſation, which may hereafter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33136:8"/> breed troubleſome apprehenſions in a Head ſo capricious as his. You may be ſecure from any fear of that kind, ſays <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> for his mind was ſo intent upon the Deſign he was to execute, of removing me from Court, that I believe there muſt have been ſome great violence offer'd him, to have made him take notice of any thing elſe. There is no remedy, now we are wholly in his power, and there is nothing to be done, but to put on a good Countenance, and to appear pleas'd with what cannot be avoided; though I would venture a thouſand Lives in the attempt of returning to the Palace, and to appear there but one hour, ſo it could be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected without blemiſh to my Honour. You know it is but two dayes ſince the Prince <hi>Athemiſtius</hi> made me a Viſit at my Lodgings; and after he had a while entertained the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany there with me, with the moſt diverting Converſation in the World, and charm'd us all into an Admiration of his Wit, he took me aſide to a Window, and with a voice lower then to be heard by any preſent but my ſelf; Madam, ſays he, I ought to be very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to you, on this Viſit, for I come to tell you, that your Beauty, (which in the ſhort time you have appear'd at Court, has inſpir'd all the Men with Love, and the Ladies with Envy) is ready to advance you above all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33136:9"/> their Paſſions, and above their Qualities too; for I come from our Imperial Maſter, to tell you, that he obſerves nothing in his Royal Palace ſo glorious as you, and that he begs (who commands us all) that you will make your Court to the Empreſs, and be conſtant at her ſide at the uſual hour, when he will take the firſt opportunity to tell you himſelf the Value he has for you. I heard this with ſeveral inward Commotions, and not without a guilty Bluſh, which diſcovered, I well enough underſtood what was the meaning of this Complement, and was going to make an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that would have better ſuited a vertuous Prudence, then the Princes Deſign; when he ſtopt me, ſaying, Madam, I muſt beg your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if I do not permit you to charge me with an Anſwer: I have executed my Commiſſion fully, and his Majeſty will better underſtand how you receive his Commands, by your obeying them, then by any words I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver from you. And thus breaking off with me, he addreſt his Diſcourſe to a Kinſwoman of mine, who had poſſeſt the Emperors Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the higheſt degree for ſome years, and rallying her at his uſual rates, upon ſome Intrigues that were not underſtood by the reſt of the Company, ſome piquant Repartées paſt between them; and at laſt the Prince ſaid to her, Madam, let us not be angry,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33136:9"/> we ſhall ſhortly be upon more equal terms, and then we may agree or fall out, as the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour takes us. This put an end to his Viſit, and put the Dutcheſs into ſuch a Fret, that the reſt of the Company taking notice of it, one after another took their Leaves and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and ſhe and I being left alone, ſhe paſſionately breaks out into theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions: I muſt no longer endure the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of <hi>Athemiſtius;</hi> his Buffoonery pleaſes, 'tis true, the Emperor; but when I let him know how often it is uneaſie to me, and with how little reſpect he treats me in all Companies, he will be made ſenſible of his Folly, in uſing his Wit againſt me, that has more powerful ways of ſecuring her Intereſt, than pratling. I could not but ſmile at theſe Threats, when I reflected on the Meſſage I had juſt then received, and ſaw that what the Prince ſaid to her, might be grounded upon the Proſpect he had of the Affair he was then engag'd in; which ſhe perceiving, Couſin, ſays ſhe, I hope the ill Uſage I have had from <hi>Athemiſtius,</hi> or the Diſorder it has put me in, is no occaſion of your appearing ſo well pleaſed. Madam, ſaid I, I have too much Intereſt in you, to be pleas'd at any thing that diſpleaſes you; but I could not without ſome diſdain, think of the Carriage of the Prince, who, though he be a man of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33136:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> extraordinary Wit, I take to be one not of ordinary Diſcretion, who after having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me with Expreſſions of the higheſt reſpect, ſhould ſo ſoon forget himſelf before my face, at that rate to uſe a Perſon of your Grandure, to whom I had the honour to be related, I ſhall frame this Action, take my Meaſures how to value him: beware of him, ſays ſhe, he makes Love to every new Face, and whatever his Succeſs be, he makes it the ſubject of his Rallery in the next Company. Keep your ſelf upon your Guard, take my Advice, and have no Converſe with the moſt uncertain Perſon in the World. She took leave, and waited on her to her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, and returning, fell into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commands <hi>Athemiſtius</hi> had brought me: I became very penſive, and retir'd into my Cabinet, and lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf up there, that I might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption examine my Heart, which I found began to be intereſſed what it would have me do, I ballanc'd a thouſand things, before I could obſerve the Scales to turn; the Precepts of Religion, and the Rules of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, in which I had been carefully inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Childhood; the faith I had given to <hi>Nicias;</hi> the Love I really have for him, and his great Merits; his lovely Perſon, and graceful Meen; his Gallantry, and obliging
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33136:10"/> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour towards me, were irreſiſtible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to confirm me in my Virtue: but on the other hand, the Glories of the moſt ſplendid Court in the World, the Charms of Wealth and Power, and the Ambition of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency, which is a moſt vehement Paſſion in our Sex: the glory of being concern'd in the Intrigues of Court and State; and the Pride to ſee the Grecian <hi>Monarch</hi> at my Feet, began to incline the Scale, and ſeem more weighty; and I was about to have call'd for you, to take your Judgment in a Caſe of this importance, when my own heart told me, if thou wouldſt be happy, preſerve thy Innocence, 'tis that will make all things pleaſant, and without it there is no Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but has more of Gall than Sweetneſs. This divine Thought ſo raviſht and poſſeſt my Soul, that I immediately reſolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all thoſe Allurements, to deſire to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what was moſt grateful to my dear <hi>Nicias;</hi> to look upon <hi>Athemiſtius,</hi> as the moſt unworthy Perſon in the World, who being of the greateſt Quality, would take upon him the baſeſt of Imployments. I determin'd to take no notice of what had paſſed between him and I, no not to you, in whom I have an entire Confidence, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the Court, and divert my ſelf in our Family, and among my Relations, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33136:11"/> are numerous and honourable enough to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford all the Delights of virtuous Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and thus having compoſed my ſelf, and paſs'd the reſt of that and the next day, after my uſual manner, as you very well know; for if you could have obſerv'd any change, I am ſure you would have enquired into the cauſe of it. Yeſternight <hi>Nicias</hi> came home ſomewhat earlier then was his Cuſtom, and with a Countenance that diſcovered more of concern, than I had ever obſerved in him, finding me alone; Madam, ſays he, read this Paper, giving me a Billet, directed to the Lord <hi>Nicias,</hi> which contained theſe words; <hi>This is a Deſign,</hi> Nicias, <hi>againſt your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which nothing can prevent, but the ſudden Removal of the Fair</hi> Nicerotis <hi>from the Court, your Sword nor your Friends, muſt not ſerve you in this occaſion, or elſe I ſhould not be the Man that could adviſe you to fly from the Danger.</hi> By this I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Secret had taken vent at Court, but reſolv'd not to ſeem to underſtand the meaning of it: I cry'd out, what Riddle is this, my Lord? What Words? What Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are theſe? What Deſign, that nothing can prevent, but my Removal? Tell me preſently the Truth, or my Fear will act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, what the cruelleſt Murtherer could deſign. There is no Danger to either of us,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33136:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid he; if we take this Advice, 'tis from ſo good a Hand, that I am certain of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of it without further enquiry: All you have to do, is to prepare for your Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to <hi>Crete</hi> with me to morrow, of which you muſt take notice to no creature alive: I have already provided a Gally with all Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies, and in the Morning, while you are dreſſing, I will make thoſe Viſits that are neceſſary for you, and ſatisfie your Friends of the manner of our Departure. He then gave order to his Servants, if any Friends came to ſup with him, they ſhould tell them, he was gone indiſpoſed to Bed, and that their Lady was ſo concerned for him, ſhe could not be Company for any one that Night. Having thus plac'd Centries and Guards upon me, he ſate ruminating a while and ſilent; but when a Sigh or extravagant Oath gave a ſudden and ſhort vent to his Paſſion, I flattered and begg'd, he would tell me the whole matter that troubl'd him; I wept when he refuſed me, and at laſt, fell into ſome Fits, which frighted him, and were really incommodious to me; the Servants were call'd, and after the help of ſome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials you brought me, he directed I ſhould go to Bed, and was not long behind me him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. I muſt confeſs, this was the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant night I had with <hi>Nicias.</hi> She was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33136:12"/> here inturrepted with a ſudden Shout of all the Slaves and Mariners of the Gally, who ſaluted the Caſtles of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abydos,</hi> as they paſs'd by them; and running to the Door of the Cabin, to know what the Matter was, when ſhe underſtood it, ſhe walk'd out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Deck, to take the view of thoſe Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo famous for the unfortunate Loves of <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander;</hi> the Hiſtory whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well known, only <hi>Nicias</hi> mentioned to his Lady; but from thence, the Captain of the Gally took occaſion to tell them the Story of a very Tragical Love-Adventure, which had lately happened in that Place, which was thus: <hi>Callippus,</hi> a Country Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, lived not far from <hi>Ceſtos,</hi> and was Lord of part of the Village, who by coming ſometimes among his Tenants there, for the management and improving his Concerns, took notice of a young Woman, who had not long been married to <hi>Dictyon</hi> a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who held a Tenement under him; to have the better pretence to frequent her, under colour of incouraging a young Man, whoſe induſtry and carefulneſs he would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten applaud, offer'd to advance him ſome Money, to fit him with the beſt Utenſils for carrying on his Trade; which being gladly accepted of by him, and his Lords kindneſs much magnified to his Wife. <hi>Callippus</hi> was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33136:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the moſt welcome man in the World, when ever he would do them the Honour to look into his Houſe, which as often as he came to the Town, he fail'd not to do; and upon pretence of erecting ſome new Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing next to the Fiſhermans Habitation, which he took in hand, to countenance his frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that place more than uſual, rather than for any other advantage he could propoſe to himſelf by it, he had opportunity to let young <hi>Phaedra</hi> know he had obſerv'd ſo much Beauty in her, that he could not but judge her worthy of a much better condition of Living, and that Compaſſion had grown at laſt, into ſo great an Affection, that he could not live, unleſs ſhe would make him a juſt return; and if ſhe would, he would provide that ſhe ſhould live in much better Faſhion than any of her Neighbours, and take ſuch care of her Credit, by finding Employment for her Huſband, that all ſhould be attributed to his thriving. The young Woman, who had been bred in a rich Family, where ſhe had learnt to value good Cloaths, and had begun to underſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of Love, but by her careful poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, was married to one of their own Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Neighbourhood, to prevent the Miſcarriages, that Girls, who have any appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Beauty, are apt to be ſeduced to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33136:13"/> in ſuch Places, was ſoon convinc'd by <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippus</hi> his Arguments, that it was better to love a Gentleman, whoſe Perſon was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough, without any other conſideration, to prevail upon the greateſt Beauties of his own Quality, then to grow old and poor in the Embraces of her Fiſherman, ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his Deſires, and with ſo good a Grace, that he, who before probably had no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deſign, then to gratifie an Appetite which young Gallants are not very deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, and to add to the Trophies of his amorous Victories, upon which men of his Age and Humour uſe to value themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came enamour'd of her to that degree, that he could not live without her, and his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity began to give ſuſpition to the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berhood, who always are maliciouſly diſpoſed to ſuſpect and defame the frequent Converſes of Perſons of different Sexes. To remedy this Inconvenience, which he ſaw would inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly cauſe the interruption of a Satisfaction he priz'd more than all other Enjoyments, he pretended to leave the care of his Buildings to his Servant, and that he had a mind to try the Hunting on the <hi>Aſian</hi> ſide of the Streight; and to that end, he agreed with <hi>Dictyon</hi> to fit up his Boat, for the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate tranſporting him three days in the Week, and attending him on the other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33136:13"/> ſide, where he might as beneficially uſe his Fiſhing as any other place, whilſt he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf follow'd another Task in the Plains near <hi>Abydos:</hi> And having conſerted the Intrigue with <hi>Phoedra,</hi> that when her Huſband at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him, ſo ſoon as the good Man was gone off from the Shore, ſhe ſhould dreſs her ſelf in thoſe Habits he had furniſh'd her with, and cloſe Vail'd, as the Cuſtom is for Perſons of Quality, take a Gondala, and paſs over to <hi>Abydos,</hi> where he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a place for her Reception, and would meet her, to entertain their Delights in more ſecurity, and with more freedom than they could at home. This was put in execution, and the Practice was continued for ſome time. The Gentleman, when he had landed in the bottom of a Bay, about half a Mile above the Town, and always giving order that the Boat ſhould lye within ſight of that Place, when he came again to the Shore, that upon a Sign made, might immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to take him in; and in the mean time, the Maſter of the Boat and his Servant might attend their Fiſhing; ſo well he thought he had projected this Contrivance, that it was impoſſible he ſhould be diſturb'd in the Execution of it; and for a while, it ſucceeded to his Wiſh, till ſome of thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Eyes, that had obſerv'd them at firſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33136:14"/> now perceiving the Scene was chang'd, ſo narrowly watched <hi>Phaedra,</hi> that they trac'd her to the Rendezvous appointed her by <hi>Callippus;</hi> where finding that true Love in effect, which they preſum'd ſo before, they did not ſpare to make themſelves merry with the Diſcourſe of it at their uſual Meetings; till at laſt, ſome who were concern'd for poor <hi>Dictyon,</hi> could not digeſt the Ralleries, that were on all occaſions plac'd upon him, advertiz'd him of the Game he ſo often car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd his Patron to hunt: The man was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, as the Natives of <hi>Thrace</hi> are, of a dark and revengeful Diſpoſition, ſoon reſolved to do himſelf right, both againſt his too kind Maſter and laſcivious Wife: And having for ſome time debated in his thoughts the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it, he took upon him a more than ordinary Kindneſs for her, and a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for him: And one day, as he paſs'd him over, he told him, that he was reſolv'd to make his Boat more convenient for him, and to contrive a Cabbin, that he and his Servants might ſit in ſecurity from the Waſh of the Sea in windy Weather, and from the daſhing of the Oars in Calms, which he might take down, and ſet up at his pleaſure, whenever he found it inconvenient to his Fiſhing, or dangerous in too high Winds. <hi>Callippus</hi> was well pleas'd with the Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33136:14"/> ſeeming care of him, and promis'd him to defray the Charge of it. He ſet his Carpenter the next day to work, and fram'd ſuch a Box, which lockt the two ſides toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it parted of it ſelf, and fell the one half on one ſide, and the other of the other, over the Boat ſides; if the Boatmen were not ready, as ſoon the Bolt was drawn, to ſet their hands to it, and take it down: This being finiſhed, the Ingenuity and Neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it very well pleaſed the amorous Gallant, who had not the leaſt ſuſpition of any Trap laid for him. Thus continued he his uſual recreation twice or thrice; after this, when <hi>Dictyon</hi> having ripen'd his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the Morning he reſolv'd to take a full Revenge of all that were Parties in the Injury done him, he takes a Bottle of Wine, and as his Cuſtom was, before he went out, took a luſty Draught of it, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying a violent Poyſon into it, pretended ſo much kindneſs to his Wife, and ſo much commended the goodneſs of the Wine, that he oblig'd her to pledge him, without much difficulty, and ſo haſtned to fit out his Boat, and attend his Maſter, who at his hour, was at the Water-ſide; he receiv'd him into the Boat very jocundly, and ſet him on Shoar on the other ſide. <hi>Callippus</hi> haſted to his Rendezvous, having given his Servants or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33136:15"/> where to hunt, and where they ſhould expect him, at the uſual hour of his Return; but he had not been long with his Miſtreſs, but ſhe began to be ſick, her Colour to come and go, and to be griped in her Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which put the two Lovers into great diſorder; for if ſhe were ſick unto Death, ſhe was no leſs afflicted; in a while, the Poyſon began to work on her Vitals, ſhe fell into fainting Fits; the Neighbours were call'd into the Aſſiſtance, the Phyſitian ſent for to the next City, but ſhe liv'd not till he came, for in ſix or ſeven hours ſhe expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in great Tortures and Convulſions; at the time of her being ill, ſhe complained on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a Draught of Wine ſhe drank in the Morning; but having no inkling of her Huſbands Jealouſie, did not at all ſuſpect him of any Malice to her. Her Lover was in great perplexity, not only the loſs of a Perſon ſo dear to him, oppreſt him with grief, but the Solicitude how to avoid the Scandal that muſt ariſe, by her dying in that Place; from whence, he knew not how to convey her to her own Houſe, privately ſet his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention upon the Rack; at laſt, he directed the Confidents of his Amours, that ſhe ſhould be buried as a Stranger, who had come to their Houſe the night before, from a Place infected with the Plague, and ſo ſhould keep
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33136:15"/> their Houſe ſhut up for ſome time, till they had ſatisfied the Magiſtrate, the Infection had not touched any one of the Family. And by that time, he would think of ſome way, to pacifie <hi>Dictyons</hi> Sorrow, and give out, that ſhe, walking on the Shoar-ſide, to take the Air, in the Evening, was taken by a <hi>Sarazen</hi> Pirat, who happen'd at that time to have purſued a ſmall light Veſſel, bound for <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to the very Streights mouth, but miſſing his Prey, and upon his Return, tacking near the Shoar, when he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied her alone, ſent off his Boat and took her away. Having ſetled his Thoughts as well as he could, and adjuſted all this Affair with his Hoſt, whom he entirely truſted, having largely obliged him, he went very melancholy out of Town, towards his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and who had attended him after their Sport was over, near an hour longer than it was uſual, and with them went on to the Shoar, where they found the Boat in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For <hi>Dictyon</hi> had long left off his Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being impatient with the Deſire of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting his Deſign, and with fear, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might diſappoint it, or the ſudden Death of his Wife, might make his Maſter apprehend ſome foul play. But when he perceived he came, he was very buſie and officious in helping him on Board; and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33136:16"/> when he was ſeated, perceiving his deep ſadneſs (though he too well underſtood the true cauſe of it) he pretended to wonder at, and became more inquiſitive into it, then his Maſters humour could well diſpence with; who, therefore gave him a Reprimand, which not being accuſtomed to receive, ſpurr'd up his Revenge, though that need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no provocation, yet diſſembling his Rage, when the Servants were ſetled, he puts off from the Shore, and gets into the Steerage of the Boat, to guide her, whilſt his two Men plyed the Oars; they were no ſooner come into the middle of the Channel, but he ſlips out the Bolt, which held the frame of the Cabbin together, and immediately the Gentleman and his two Servants fell over the Boat, and it being a dark night, were all three drown'd. <hi>Dictyon</hi> would make his Servants believe it was an accident; but they ſhould all ſuffer Death for it, if they were taken, and therefore told them, if they would fly with them, they might preſerve themſelves. That they would go to Shoar, and he would fetch what Money, and what valuable things he had, and immediately go to Sea, and recover ſome of the Iſlands poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> who were Enemies to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and very powerful at Sea, by whom they would be gladly received. This
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33136:16"/> ſeeming the beſt thing they could do, in the Condition they were, it was conſented to; and bringing the Boat to Shoar, the Maſter and one of his Men went to his Houſe, and finding not his Wife, ſeemed to be angry, and to want the Keys of ſome Boxes, and broke open what ever was lock't in the Houſe, and ſeizing on a Purſe of Gold, and ſome other good things, wherewith his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Liberality had enriched his Wife, and loading his Servant with ſuch Proviſions as were neceſſary, he goes out of doors towards the Boat. When he came to it, he found not the Servant he left there; but having not leiſure to wait for him (being under ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of a Diſcovery) he haſtily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows his Carriage aboard, and with the help of him that was with him, he put off to Sea. The vigor wherewith they apply'd themſelves to their Oars, carried them many Leagues, before the Night fell; at which time the Moon being riſen, had ſufficiently fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd their purpoſe; but that divers Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of rough weather approaching, oblig'd them to put in at the next convenient Creek; where beſtowing themſelves under ſhelter of a hanging Rock, after they had ſtruck a Light, they fell to the Proviſions they had brought from home, little ſuſpecting the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of that Banquet. For in the hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33136:17"/> of their Diſpatch, the Servant (as by the juſt Judgment of Heaven) had taken that Bottle, whereof his Maſters Wife had drank ſo fatal a Draught, which filling up and bringing aboard, prov'd ſhare of their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; the dire effects of which, after ſhort repoſe, awakt them, to ſleep for ever: the Bodies, together with the Treaſure in the Boat, prov'd an Object of no leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than joy, to ſome neighbouring Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who deſcending to their uſual Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Sea-ſide, ſoon after diſcovered them.—This Relation of the Captains, though liſtned unto with equal Attention, was with various Sentiments reflected on by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> and <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> he juſtifying the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Dictyon,</hi> and applauding ſo nice a ſenſe of Honour, in a Perſon of ſuch mean Degree, whilſt ſhe ſilently commiſerated the Misfortune of the Lovers. Her Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by reaſon of being unaccuſtomed to Sea, was now ſo much increaſed, that for the reſt of that day, and part of the next, ſhe kept within her Cabbin. The Veſſel was all the while follow'd by ſo brisk a Gale, that in leſs time than cou'd be propos'd, they arriv'd where they intended. <hi>Nicerotis</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Prudence, and applying her ſelf to her wonted Subtlety, joyns with <hi>Nicias,</hi> in Acknowledgments to the Captain of the Gally,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33136:17"/> for his Conduct and Care, and diſſembling a Joy, which ſhe knew would pleaſe her Lord, was before-hand with him, in giving the Welcome to <hi>Cydon.</hi> The Lord <hi>Emathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> being informed of their Arrival, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately deſcends to the Port to receive them, with ſuch Attendance of Chariots and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as was ſuitable to their Quality and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him; ſo diſcharging the Captain well preſented, he conducts them to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Place appointed for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, was an extraordinary Fabrick, which in the original Deſign of it, contained not only an Oratory and Court of Sacrifice for the Deity there in former times ador'd, but alſo ſpacious Manſions for ſuch Prieſts as were employed in thoſe Rites. Which ancient Seat of Idolatry and Superſtition, together with the reſt of the ſame ſort, had, ſince days of better Knowledge, been demoliſht or alter'd, and their rich appendant Poſſeſſions, and were given as Rewards to ſuch Perſons as had merited of the Empire. This Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with the Revenues belonging to it, had been conferred on the Anceſtors of <hi>Amathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> for eminent Services by them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, who, according to their ſeveral Fancies, built it up in ſeveral Ages; ſo that that though it wanted that regular neatneſs, which the modern Builder ſo much affect;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33136:18"/> yet the ſtatelineſs of the Rooms, ſhewing the large Souls of the Lords of that Family, and the convenient diſpoſition of the Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, largely ſupplied that Defect. The Apartment appointed for <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> was one of the laſt built parts of the Palace, and faced a large Garden, of three hundred Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits ſquare, encompaſſed with a very high Wall; out of her Anti-Chamber, opened a folding Door, into the midſt of a Terrace Walk, of the length of one ſide of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, paved with Black and White Marble; from which was a Deſcent of ſix large Steps, of the ſame Materials into the Walks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which were laid with a groſs ſort of Gravel of various Colours, ſo faſt, ſo bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſo ſmooth, that it ſeems at firſt view, to reſemble that curious <hi>Moſaick</hi> Work that adorns the Pavement of the Quire, in the great Cathedral of <hi>Sancta So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> between the Walks were Graſs-Plots. <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/> 
                  <hi>[Theſe Marks ſhews a great Breach in the Original, by the Defacements of the Writing of more than a Page.]</hi> In the midſt was a large Baſon of black Marble, about thirty Cubits in Compaſs, exquiſitely poliſhed, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33136:18"/> by the Effigies at large, of eleven of the Twelve Signs of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> all made of white Marble; the Twelfth, being the Fiſhes, was placed within the little Sea, as in their proper Elements. In the middle was placed a large Pedeſtal, which to the ſurface of the Water was a ragged piece of Marble, as it was digg'd out of the Quarry, topp'd with a greeniſh coloured Stone, cut after the form of the Iſland of <hi>Crete,</hi> with all the Creeks, Harbours and Rivers, and all the Hills and Mountains of it; with the little Figures of the hundred Cities, for which that Iſland was once famous, cut in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral coloured Stones, and inchaſed into it, in the ſeveral Diſtances and Poſitions, in which the real ones were placed. In the midſt was the Mountain <hi>Ida,</hi> out of which roſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſmall Streams that fill'd thoſe Channels, made to repreſent the Rivers, and ran ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their proper Courſes into the Sea; on the top of the Mountain was placed the Statue of a Woman, of the pureſt Alabaſter, holding in her Arms the Figure of a Child, ſucking at one Breaſt, whilſt the other ſpout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Stream of Water into the Baſon; about her Head, was a Chaplet of Ivy, very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the Stone being artificially ſtain'd to the Colour of the Leaf; ſhe was naked to the Waſte, but from thence to the middle of her
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33136:19"/> Thighs hung a Goatskin, being the Dreſs of the <hi>Bacchanal,</hi> to whom the Poets feign <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> was ſent to be nurſed; this was a piece of that admired Statuary <hi>Praxite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> who lived a thouſand years before, and being found by <hi>Amathius</hi> his Father, in the Ruins of the Temple, when he was clearing a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, was for the Excellency of the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, repaired and ſet up to view, though it had been formerly the Idol of that Place, as may well be judged, being the Image of <hi>Jupiters</hi> Nurſe, giving ſuck to the young God, the Honour of whoſe foſtering Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, has attributed to this Country. The Walls of the Garden were <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/> In the midſt of the Wall, oppoſite to the Terrace, a large pair of Gates opened into a Garden twice as ſpacious, wherein were planted all the choiceſt Fruits of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> it was divided into four Squares by a croſs cloſe Walk, the South-end of which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened into a delicate Grotto, deſigned for a Retreat from the raging Heats of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; it was a Room of eight Sides, each ſide being ſix Cubits in breadth, the Diameter of the whole <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/> The North-end opened into a Banqueting Room, at one ſide whereof, was a Door that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33136:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> gave paſſage into a private Street of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs; the Eaſt and the croſs Walk led to a Door that opened into a fair Vineyard, in which were <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/> 
                  <hi>Nicerotis</hi> was at firſt well pleaſed with theſe pretty Accommodations; but that Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did not laſt long: her temper inclined her more to the Delights of Converſation than to Melancholy, though curious and artificial Solitudes, yet did ſhe not forget to reflect upon the Conveniences that theſe Places might upon occaſion afford her. She had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Viſits of the Relations of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of ſuch other Perſons of Quality in that City, who were any way obliged to make them, and it was time ſhe ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay that Debt, and make Acquaintances in a Place, where ſhe was no longer to be a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Her firſt Viſit was the Court of <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucius,</hi> then Exurch or Chief Governour of the Iſland, under the Emperour <hi>Iſiaacius.</hi> He was a Perſon of great Magnificence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Favour of his Maſter, which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in a great Proportion, he was Lord of a vaſt Patrimonial Eſtate, which enabled him to keep one of the beſt Provincial Courts in the whole Empire: His own Family was numerous; his Daughters were arrived to that Age, in which their Sex begins to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33136:20"/> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their Priviledges, and their Beauties gave them no unreaſonable Pretences, to think they had the Prerogative of all others of the Country, as well in right of their Perfections as Quality; his three Sons were now all well accompliſhed, but the Eldeſt, <hi>Leontius,</hi> was a Perſon who had given thoſe Proofs of his Courage and Abilities to the World, that he was deſervedly reputed one of the braveſt Gentlemen alive; his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the Wars, and in his Amours, were always glorious, and in both his Merits and his Fortune ſtill made it diſputable which of them moſt promoted his Conqueſts. The Authority of the Father, the Virtue and Prudence of the Mother, the Gallantry and Beauty of the Children, drew together ſuch a Concourſe of the Nobility and Gentry, that <hi>Lycias</hi> his Court had no ſmall reſemblance of the Emperors, and yet when <hi>Nicerotis</hi> firſt appear'd there, ſhe preſently became the Idol of one Sex, but the Envy of the other: The Ladies, who could ſpy no fault in her Face, in her Stature, or Meen, in her Wit, or Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in a ſhort time began to blame her Conduct, the Gallants of the Court and Town made their Reſort where ſhe frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhe was deſired of every one that had Quality enough, to pretend to her Favour; Comedies and Balls were more frequently
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33136:20"/> appointed then it was uſual in <hi>Cydon;</hi> and ſome of the Court-Wits, who would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves thought enough to write Plays, made Prologues, to give</p>
               <p>At every publick Meeting, ſome one or other took the opportunity to pay her ſome extraordinary of his Reſpect. <hi>Leontius</hi> had ſo many Advantages over all the reſt, that it is not to be wondred at, if his Addreſſes met the beſt Reception. He viſited her often; he omitted no occaſion of ſeeing her, either in publick or private, and gave her ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of his Paſſion, as could not but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince her of it; he made Preſents to <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and by that means had her whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in Penſion; ſo that ſhe could take no Reſolutions, but what were in his Favour, nor diſcover her Sentiments, but immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had notice of them: For <hi>Philenis</hi> was the only Perſon ſhe had intire confidence in, and for whom ſhe had nothing of reſerve. One Morning, ſays <hi>Nicerotis</hi> to her, How impoſſible is it to reſiſt the Courtſhip of <hi>Leontius? Nicias,</hi> ſince his coming to his own Country, having tempted me from mine, either deſpites me as a Stranger, or has received ſome former commerce, or has abandoned himſelf to the Debauch; I have little of his Company, and his Kindneſſes are both rarer and leſs agreeable than formerly.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33136:21"/> What reaſon is there I ſhould reſerve my ſelf for him only, that never gives himſelf to me, but when he knows not what elſe to do with himſelf? None in the World, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Philenis,</hi> no more then that you ſhould faſt, when he does not come home to Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; if he neglects, you muſt therefore neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect your ſelf: If he has found out other ways of paſſing his time to his Content, does it oblige you to ſpend your days in miſery and Complaints? Alas, Madam! Life is an uncertain thing, and at the beſt, thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of it that are deſigned by Fate for Happineſs, are ſo few, that to let any of them paſs unimployed, is an incorrigible Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and a loſs that is but meanly recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, by the Opinion one gains among thoſe only that are paſt the reliſhing of Pleaſures. I did not think, ſays <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon could be given for Sinning; I thought the moſt could be ſaid for it, was that paſſion might excuſe Women in Love, as it does Men in Murder: But be it as it will, my heart has betrayed me to <hi>Leontius,</hi> and I bluſh to think what his ſucceſs will be at the next aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault. It was not long before the diligent Intelligencer ſent advice of this to <hi>Leontius.</hi> The hour of his Viſit was aſſigned, and all things ſo contrived, that he muſt needs be infinitely happy, if there were as much felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33136:21"/> in fruition as Men fancy to themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand. However theſe two Lovers were ſo well ſatisfied with one another, that they lived in an exact Correſpondence; no Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, no Capricious, no little Peeks di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed good Humour, no unhappy Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents put them out of their Meaſures; till <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> weary of ſo eaſie delights, took a Freak in her head, and would needs appoint her Gallant a Rendezvous abroad; ſhe told him, ſhe had by accident been at one of the Gardens near the Town, where they ſell their Fruit, and the choiceſt of all ſorts, and where was the prettieſt Labyrinth for Lovers to loſe themſelves in that could be imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſhe deſired he would meet her there the next day, an hour before Sun, without any Retinue, that they might not be known; he eaſily agreed to any thing ſhe propoſed, and being a Frollick of her own, ſhe was the earlieſt up, ſhe and her Woman put on the Dreſs of the ſpruceſt of thoſe ſort of Girls, that carry Fruit among Perſons of Quality, at the Theaters and publick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zades, and with their Baskets on their Arms, went privately out of her Lodgings to the Place appointed; they knockt up the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diners, and demanded to have entrance, and have ſuch and ſuch Fruits gathered; the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows went about what they were directed,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33136:22"/> and one of them a luſty young Springle, caſting his Eye upon theſe new Cuſtomers, and obſerving a more than ordinary Beauty in them, when he had gathered what he was bid, preſented them their Baskets, and <hi>Philenis</hi> looking for Money to pay them, pull'd out a piece of Gold and offered him; but the Youth laying hold of <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> ſaid, he had rather be paid in another Coin, and began rudely to kiſs her; whilſt they were ſtruggling, <hi>Leontius</hi> came in, but not thinking himſelf concerned, was walking in, when the Lady called him to her Aſſiſtance; he knew the Voice, and turning about with ſome diſorder, advanced in haſt towards the Scuffle, which the Fellow perceiving, left off his Rudeneſs and ſtept aſide, and ſhe addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her ſelf to him, ſaid, Sir, I had like to have paid too dear for this Fruit, and it is but juſt I ſhould preſent it to my Reſcuer. He thought he knew the Sound, but the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe had ſo altered the Perſon, that looking on her as one of the Condition ſhe appeared in, he ſaid, he had no mind to eat any ſo early, and was turning away from her, when ſhe laid hold of his Arm, and ſaid; Sir, here is ſomewhat you will have a mind to if you look upon it; this little Importunity, with the Tone in which ſhe ſpoke, and the Glance of her Eye opened his; <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> ſays he, I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33136:22"/> did not think I ſhould have had ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Rival, I muſt chaſtiſe the Inſolence of this Fellow; ſays ſhe; I believe his fear of you has already done that, and his Ignorance may excuſe him from any other Puniſhment; and beſides, it's beſt for us he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnified by that, for we have no deſire to be known here; ſhe took him by the hand, and they walked into the Labyrinth, <hi>Philenis</hi> following them at a diſtance, and after ſome entertainment there, they return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and went out of the Garden; he waited on her to the Vineyard behind her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, where, when ſhe was entred, he went of to the Place he appointed his Servants and Chariot to attend him; after he parted from her, he began to reflect upon his Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings Adventure, he could not conceive her Deſign, to give her ſelf and him that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to no end, but the hazard of giving Scandal; he judged ſhe had not been long enough in the Country, to have uſed this way of Aſſignation to other Perſons, that had not his Opportunities: he was not at all ſatisfied with her, and concluded it a light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, which he could not approve of. The young Gardiner <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who after his Fright was a little over, found the reliſh of the raviſhed Kiſſes on his Lips, ſet himſelf to watch the two Women and this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33136:23"/> Gentleman; he followed them at a diſtance, till he obſerved where the Women entred, and then returned, with a thouſand imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his Noddle, that a long time after diſquieted him. <hi>Leontius</hi> continued his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Viſits, and the Ladies Charms quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put away the Diſguſt he had taken, and he was more in Love then ever; yet a while after it happened, that being engaged in ſome Affair, that he could not free himſelf from, he miſſed an appointment given him; <hi>Nicerotis</hi> ſpent that time very unquietly, ſhe began to be jealous, that <hi>Leontius</hi> his Paſſion might be growing cool, or that he had ſome new Intrigue; ſhe impeached <hi>Philenis,</hi> for ſo often magnifying his Riches and good Qualities, ſhe accuſed him of Infidelity, and ſaid, that a Man in his Circumſtances, that was guilty of the leaſt neglect, was never to be pardoned, or at leaſt, not till he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ten-fold in the ſame kind; ſhe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him ſeverely, and was going to paſs the dreadful Sentence of Indifferency againſt him; when ſhe checkt her ſelf; well, ſays ſhe, 'tis folly to determine any thing of him, till I am truly informed of all the Aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Crime; if the Expreſſions of my Reſentment be not proportioned to his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, he will think me eaſie to be impoſed on, and he will take a Liberty in a ſhort
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33136:23"/> time, to uſe me as a Wife, which none muſt ever have a Priviledge to do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But <hi>Nicias;</hi> I muſt know the ſecret of this Abſence, and I will be the Diſcoverer my ſelf, for you are too much his Friend, to be entirely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied on in the Inquiry. This Evening a new Habit was brought home for the Page, which was ordered againſt the next ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Solemnity; do you ſend for it into your Chamber, on pretence, that I have directed ſomewhat to be altered about it, and let that, with the other Accoutre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch an Officer, be provided ready in the Garden-houſe, in the Morning, by the dawn of day; I will carry him a Viſit, as from my ſelf, and by that Pretence, will learn among his Servants, how he ſpent this Night. The next day very early, this was put in execution; the Lady was dreſt in her Pages Habit, left <hi>Philenis</hi> in the Garden-houſe to attend her Return, and goes to the Palace of the <hi>Exarch,</hi> and coming to <hi>Leon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his Apartment, ſhe went up into his Anti-Chamber very briskly, where two of the Officers of his Chamber were attending half aſleep; but being rouzed by the buſling the young Gentleman made, they beckned him to make leſs noiſe, which he taking no notice of, advanced in the ſame manner to them, and deſired to be admitted to their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33136:24"/> Lord, with a Meſſage he had to deliver from the Lady <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> The Officers ſeeing this Rudeneſs, told him, they believed he had not been long in the Service of any Perſon of Quality, or he would have underſtood better, how he ought to make his Approaches towards them. They ſaid, their Lord went late to Bed, and that none ſhould come in till he call'd; ſhe was incenſed at this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſo little ſatisfactory to her, to the Point ſhe had given her ſelf ſo much trouble to be reſolved in. She preſt between them to the Door, and knockt hard, which made the Gentlemen lay hold of her, to take her away by force, and turn her out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; But ſhe ſtruggling with them, made ſuch a ſtir, that the Lord call'd to know what was the matter? and one going in, he angerly askt what meant that noiſe, who was told the whole Rudeneſs of the Page; he ordered his Admittance, and being willing to receive the Meſſage privately, commanded his Servant to ſtay without and ſhut the Door. The Struggling had raiſed a moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Red in her Face, and ſo diſordered her Hair, that was truſt up under a Peruke, that the long Trails of it falling down as ſhe made her Bows, in advancing to the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; he needed no other Diſcovery, but raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in his Bed, he reached out his Arm
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33136:24"/> and pull'd her to him, and embracing her, after a thouſand Kiſſes, told her, Madam, I confeſs the Crime you come to reproach me with, and declare the commiting it, was it ſelf a cruel Puniſhment, ſince it prevented the happineſs of ſeeing you laſt night. Thoſe are no Puniſhments, my Lord, ſays ſhe, which we chooſe, and ſince you have choſen other Imployments for that little time you promiſed to ſet apart for me, I come to eaſe you of the trouble of making any Excuſes, and to reſign back into your hands, all your Obligations and Vows of Perſeverance; it is better to beſtow Liberty upon the Priſoner that has broke his Chains, than to leave him the Glory of having been his own Deliverer; you ſhall never have it to boaſt of, that you have forſaken <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> ſhe was proceeding to more bitterneſs, when he interrupted her with a Sigh: Ah Madam! ſays he, you are too ſudden, in paſſing your Judgment on me, before you hear me. It was an unfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen and unreſiſtible Accident that kept me from you, and when you hear it, you will confeſs that you ought not to be angry with me, unleſs you will impute Misfortune as a Crime, and believe Puniſhments were deviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Unhappy, not for the Guilty. I was laſt night invited to a Treat, by ſome of the Officers of my Army, I do not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33136:25"/> often engage in thoſe Entertainments, but to endear thoſe brave men, who are ready to venture their Lives at my Command, I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpend an hour or two at the moſt, chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with them; the time appointed for this Meeting, and the ordinary meaſure of my Stay with them, agreed ſo well with my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment with you, that I could not refuſe them; but as we were ready to break up, your Lord came in upon us, either wanting other Company, or being in queſt of ſome of ours. We were all very forward to pay him thoſe Reſpects that are due to his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and to the Reputation he juſtly holds among Souldiers, and a Glaſs or two going round, had ſo improved the Humour, he had put himſelf into ſome other place, that he would take upon him to give Law to us all, which I would not have allow'd to any body, not ſo nearly related to you; he preſſed ſo upon us, that without being rude to him, we could not break up, till we all were become as unruly as he, and I believe 'tis not two hours ſince we parted. This ſays ſhe (kiſſing him, rather to try if his Zeal juſtified his Words, than out of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at that time) ſhall ſerve for once; but for the future, when any thing is preferrible by you to my Company, I ſhall believe you begin not to value it. Madam, ſays he, I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33136:25"/> refer my ſelf to my future Services, which ſhall ſufficiently clear me of all Suſpition; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe terms, I leave you to your Reſt, ſays ſhe, which I perceive is now more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for you, than any further Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I refer to our Meeting this Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: he would have kept her, but ſhe ſprang from the Bed-ſide, and he called his Servants, and commanded the diſcreeteſt of them, to wait on that young Gentleman out of the Palace, but firſt, that they ſhould beg her Pardon for their Incivility to her, and that from thenceforth they ſhould not at any time refuſe admittance to any that came from <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> whatever Orders they had given them in the general. She departed pretty well ſatisfied, and return'd to the Garden-houſe where <hi>Philaenis</hi> attended her, and the Lord compoſed himſelf to reſt as ſoon as he could, for the Reflections he could not avoid to make upon this Adventure; about three hours after, when he was riſing, <hi>Polyphon,</hi> one of thoſe Commanders who had been with him over night, came to viſit him, and to enquire how he did, after that unuſual Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh he had been engag'd in. He told him, he ſuffered deeply for that Exceſs, and was reſolved not to allow himſelf the like Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty again for any Reſpect; <hi>Polyphon</hi> told him, it was for want of uſe, and he would find it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33136:26"/> to agree with him after a little Practice; I had rather, ſaid <hi>Leontius,</hi> you and the reſt of my Friends would find it as inconvenient as I do, for I look upon Drinking, to be a Vice as unbecoming Souldiers as any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion whatſoever. My Lord, ſays he, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, that is a Doctrine will hardly obtain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, whilſt we are out of Action; in time of War 'tis enough to be Sober; in Peace, we have nothing elſe to do but drink and make Love. Does your Lordſhip hear nothing of the Emperors Deſigns this Spring? I heard, ſaid <hi>Leontius,</hi> ſome Gallies of the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> have contrary to the late Peace, made a Deſcent on the Coaſt of <hi>Cilici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and that they are preparing to ſet out a great Fleet to Sea; but how the Emperor reſents it, we do not yet underſtand. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few days after, <hi>Leontius</hi> received Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to repair to Court, to take the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Squadron of the Fleet, that was preparing to puniſh the Inſolencies of thoſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and ſome days afterwards, he told <hi>Polyphon,</hi> in the Diſcourſe of his Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for his Voyage, that he had been engaged in an Affair of Love, that would have been troubleſome to him upon this occaſion, if his Paſſion had not been a little rebated, by ſome indiſcretions of the Perſon he was engaged with. But, ſays he, I leave
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33136:26"/> amongſt you, one of the moſt beautiful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the World, and if ſhe were not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſo importune, the moſt agreeable. My Lord, ſays <hi>Polyphon,</hi> you need not name her, for your Amour has not been as great a Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as you imagined, and if you abandon your Intereſts in her, every one may, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſobliging you, pretend to his own Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages.—I am not ſo ill natured, ſays <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontius,</hi> to envy my Friends their good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, nor ſo great a Fool, to expect to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine a Humour, that I know hates all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. And ſince I can make her no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of my Return, it is juſt I ſhould leave her to her own Liberty. This was a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Evidence of an Indifferency, that not long before, all the World could not have convinced him, he ſhould ever be guilty of. The News of the Town, carried the Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his being commanded to Court, before he himſelf brought it to <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> it put her into a thouſand Troubles, which ſhe did not long defer to let him know, for his Affairs having kept him one day from wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on her, the next Morning he received this Billet from her. <hi>You need not joyn <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſs with the neceſſity of your leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, the one or the other has Force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to kill</hi> Nicerotis. This paſſionate Reprehenſion of his Neglect, made him
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33136:27"/> haſten to wait on her, to make the beſt Excuſes <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44-95" type="pages">
               <p>Says <hi>Nicias</hi> to <hi>Glaneus,</hi> I have been told of the Liberty <hi>Polyphon</hi> has taken, in a certain Company, to ſpeak of ſome Deſigns he has upon my Wife, and with ſome dark Reflections upon the Departure of <hi>Leontius;</hi> I am not of a Spirit ſo weak, as to be ſubject to Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies; or if I were, could ſo mean a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be a reaſonable Cauſe of it? yet I think his Impertinence ought not to go unchaſtiſed, and I am reſolved to take the firſt occaſion that I can, to fix a Quarrel upon him; but to avoid the being talked of, as a jealous Coxcomb, I muſt have you to begin it, and I will come in as a Second. <hi>Glaneus</hi> was a Perſon the forwardeſt in the World, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of that kind; he had paſſed over many Encounters and Duels, with ſuch ſucceſs, as made him very haughty, and deſirous of getting Honour that way, and on the other ſide, had warned thoſe that kept him Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to be wary in their Converſation, not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33136:27"/> to give him a Pretence, ſo that he had lived a long time quiet, and began to obtain the name of a ſociable and well conditioned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman; but being put in mind by his Friend, of the way he had formerly ſo prided him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he preſently took Fire, and was all of a Flame, and leaving <hi>Nicias,</hi> told him, he would give him an Account of his Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next Morning; the reſt of the day, he ſpent in finding out <hi>Polyphon,</hi> who at laſt he found engaged in Company of Ladies; he could hardly refrain from making the Quarrel there, but he judged that fitter to be done by one that had not a mind to fight, then ſuch a one whoſe greateſt concern it was not to be prevented; yet hardly diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his Deſign, in a huffing away, he askt him where they might meet in the Evening? and being told he would be in ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany at a Tavern, he named to him (where they had appointed to play off ſome pieces of Gold) after ſome high flown Complements, paſſed upon the Ladies, <hi>Glaneus</hi> took his leave, and carried his Intelligence to <hi>Nicias,</hi> at the Time and Place named, they found the Company met together, and pretty well advanced in Play; <hi>Polyphon</hi> had loſt, and began to be uneaſie (as Gameſters for the moſt part are, when they have had an ill Run, and accuſing Fortune on the Dice, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33136:28"/> 
                  <hi>Glaneus</hi> took the Occaſion that he found favourable enough for his Deſign, and in a rough way of Rallery, excuſed Fortune, and caſt the blame of his Loſſes upon his Folly, and want of Judgment, and pulling out a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Gold, ſet it him to throw at, which, as he prepared to do, <hi>Glaneus</hi> took up his Gold, and put it in his Pocket, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied this Action with ſome diſrepective Geſtures; at which, <hi>Polyphon</hi> being juſtly provokt, told him, he was not a Perſon to be ſo uſed, and that he muſt lay down his Money, and after he had try'd his Fortune at that, he muſt give him ſatisfaction for the Affront: <hi>Glaneus</hi> ſcornfully told him, he was not diſpoſed to Play<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at that time, but for what other Satisfaction he expected, he might demand and have it; the other was laying hand on his Sword, when <hi>Ariſtander</hi> ſtept to him and held him; whilſt <hi>Gephyrius</hi> did the like to <hi>Glaneus,</hi> intending to pacifie them; But <hi>Nicias,</hi> whoſe Deſign was to blow the Coal, ſaid, things could not arrive to that height among men of Honour, but they muſt go further; when <hi>Satirius,</hi> a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not inferiour to him in Quality, a Friend to <hi>Polyphon,</hi> and as prompt as any of them in the like Adventures, ſaid, he was of his mind, and taking him by the Hand, told him, he ſhould be concerned if he pleaſed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33136:28"/> which the others hearing, quitted one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and preſently made a Parley to meet the next Morning on Horſe-back, in a Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, about a Mile diſtant from the City; having agreed this, to the end they might appear pacified, and take off the Suſpitions of the Servants of the Houſe, they drank a Glaſs or two of Wine to each other, and ſo parted every one to his own Lodgings, to give Order for their preparation againſt the next day; by the Dawn they were all moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, pretending ſeverally, that they were to meet ſome Country Gentlemen, who had given them notice over night, they had har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd (<gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/>) a wild Boar in a Wood, about four mile off the Town (another way then that which they had appointed) and that they would be there with their Dogs, and Nets by break of day; they took each of them a Foot-man with his Hunting Spear, and going out ſeveral ways, when they came to the foot of a Hill, beyond which was the Place they were to meet at, they placed their Servants, with charge, they ſhould not ſtir ground till they were called; then they advanced over the Hill, without other Arms then a Horſe-mans Sword and a Javelin (the Weapons in that time, only in uſe in ſingle Combats, fought on Horſe-back) they were all Perſons of great Courage, and every one
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33136:29"/> ſtriving to be the earlieſt, they did not ſtay long one for another. When they were all come, after a few words importing their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that they might loſe no time in the Diſpatch of the Buſineſs they were met a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, they every one turned their Horſes, and galloping a little diſtance, wheeled about, and then drawing their Swords, and poiſing their Javelins, they almoſt at one inſtance delivered them; <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> to his ſhare it fell to fight; <hi>Gephyrius</hi> received his Enemies Javelin in his Bridle-Arm, which piercing the fleſhy part of it, and paſſing between the Skin of his Side, and the Ribs, ſeemed to have gone through his Body, whilſt his Jave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin lighted on the Thigh of <hi>Gephyrius,</hi> and piercing it and the Skirts of the Saddle, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Horſes ſide, which ſo gald him, that he began to plunge; when <hi>Ariſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> coming up in his Career, with his Sword elevated, he had had a great advantage over his Adverſary, had not the unrulineſs of the Horſe broke all his Girts, and thrown the Rider with the Saddle to the Ground. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtander,</hi> at this ſucceſs, was about to have alighted, either to have ſuccoured his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, if he were dangerouſly wounded, or to have made an end of the Fight on Foot; when looking about, to ſee what was the Succeſs of the reſt of the Parties, he ſaw
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33136:29"/> 
                  <hi>Nicias</hi> and <hi>Satirius</hi> engaged very cloſe with their Swords, dealing their Stroaks with great fury and nimbleneſs; when <hi>Satirius</hi> by the agility of a well dreſt Numidian, on which he was mounted, had gain'd the Crooper of <hi>Nicias: Ariſtander</hi> ſpying his Friends danger, flew like lightning to his Succour, and preſenting his Point to <hi>Satiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who ſtepping ſhort, put himſelf in his defence againſt this New-comer, gave <hi>Nicias</hi> the opportunity to turn again upon his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; they were then two to one, but were too generous to take the Advantage, yet <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirius</hi> preſſed them hard, they only defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, told him, it was fit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat ſhould ceaſe, there was enough done to vindicate their Honours, and they did not meet there to butcher one another, but to try their Courage; in this while <hi>Gephirius,</hi> who had drawn the Javelin out of his Thigh, yet not ſenſible of the loſs of Blood, nor wholly diſabled by his Wound, came to take part with <hi>Satirius,</hi> and began to attack his firſt man, who ſtarting a little off, alighted from his Horſe, to put himſelf in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual condition with his Adverſary, and as he advanced towards him, <hi>Glaneus</hi> came gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loping between them, and calling aloud to <hi>Nicias,</hi> and <hi>Satirius,</hi> deſired them to ſtop their Fury, for <hi>Polyphon</hi> was fallen dead from
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33136:30"/> his Horſe, and they were now the greater number, and perhaps there was Blood enough ſpilt already. At the news of <hi>Polyphons</hi> Fall, they all made a little pauſe, and <hi>Satirius</hi> looking about, ſpyed a Party of about twenty Horſe, galloping over the Hill. It is not your being three to two, ſays he, ſhould have prevailed with me, to have quitted you ſo eaſily, but that I ſee more Company coming in to take part with us, than you or I wiſh. See where a Party comes, pointing that way no doubt, by the Command of the <hi>Exarch,</hi> to ſeize us; let us mount <hi>Gephirius</hi> on <hi>Polyphons</hi> Horſe, and ride away to the Town, to have our Wounds dreſt, and ſend the Servants to bring off the Body of <hi>Polyphon.</hi> This being neceſſary Counſel, and no time of Debate left them, how more ceremoniouſly they ſhould treat the dead Body they put in execution, and away they gallopt a full Carreer, to the Place where the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants were placed, and ſent <hi>Gephirius</hi> and <hi>Polyphons</hi> two Men, to bring off the Horſe and Body of the Slain; every one haſted to his own Lodgings, and the Condition they were in, required it, they had all of them loſt a great deal of blood, and ſome were dangerouſly wounded; <hi>Nicias</hi> had ſeveral Wounds, but one eſpecially, between two of the Ribs of his left ſide, that though it did
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33136:30"/> not ſeem at firſt to be the moſt conſiderable, yet in effect, afterwards it proved of very ill conſequence to him. <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> by the great effuſion of Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and the feſtering of his Wound, was caſt into a Feaver, which kept him a long time fixed to his Bed, and put him in a Condition, that made his Friends fear he would hardly riſe out of it. <hi>Nicias</hi> was no ſooner dreſt, but he began to think of the ſeaſonable aſſiſtance <hi>Aristander</hi> had brought him, when <hi>Satirius</hi> was at the point to have diſpatcht him, and conſidering he had been the cauſe of this Quarrel, in which <hi>Ariſtander</hi> had no concern, but from his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental being in the Company, when it was begun, and conſidering their old Friendſhip, which had grown up from their Childhood, and his Quality, which was very eminent, he immediately ſent a Gentleman to viſit him, and to enquire of his Condition: <hi>Aristan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> Wounds were dreſt, but his loſs of Blood had ſo weakned him, that it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by his Phyſicians, that none ſhould be ſuffered to come at him, that might give him occaſion of ſpending any of thoſe few Spirits that were left him, ſo that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was fain to return with ſuch Errand as the Chyrurgions would give him. The next morning <hi>Nicias</hi> was very inquiſitive of his Friends Condition, and not being ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33136:31"/> with the Account that was given him, he call'd for his Lady, and told her how much ſhe was obliged to his Valour, that had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded him with ſo much Gallantry, when his Enemy had the advantage of him, and enjoyned her that day to make him a Viſit, and to have the ſame concern for <hi>Ariſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> Recovery, that ſhe had of his: ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged herſelf of this Commiſſion very obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly, and the firſt time ſhe went to ſee him, ſaid ſo many endearing things to him, and ſo wittily expreſſed her Reſentment, and the Opinion ſhe had of his Courage, that he began to think that Blood was not ill ſpent, that had purchaſed him the Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of one of the greateſt Beauties of the Age. His Wounds were long in healing, and he was longer before he recovered ſtrength enough to go abroad, and perhaps he kept his Chamber longer then he needed, becauſe he would not loſe the ſatisfaction of entertaining her every day for an hour while he did ſo, and when he was well, he found himſelf wounded in a more ſenſible part than his Enemies Sword had reached unto. But <hi>Nicerotis</hi> after a while, thought ſhe loſt too much time in this deſolate State ſhe was in: during the weakneſs of her Lord, ſhe was obliged by the Decencies and Rules of a Conjugal State, to paſs the whole days in his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33136:31"/> Chamber, to receive all her Viſits there, and could have no Converſation, but what he or the old Lady <hi>Sophonia</hi> his Mother, or ſome of his Relations were privy to, and the only Viſits ſhe was permitted to make, being to <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> who was not in a Condition to make thoſe warm Addreſſes that were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to engage a Perſon of her humour. She reſolved to take her ſatisfaction in any manner ſhe could; ſhe had entertained a little before the Combat, a ſprightly young Fellow, in quality of a Footman, who from the time of being entertained in her Service, had expreſſed all the diligence and obſervance that was poſſible; he was of a middle Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, well ſet, active of Body, and of a ruddy Complexion, and when ſhe began to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him, ſhe ſoon perceived that he uſed to look on her often, with more concern, than Servants of that ſort have audacity to do, on Perſons of her Rank; ſhe began to think ſhe had ſeen his Face ſomewhere before he came into her Family, and this inflamed her Deſires, and ſhe began to fancy he might be ſome Perſon of better Condition then he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, who, overcome by his Paſſion for her, had in that Diſguiſe, ſought to be near her Perſon. Whilſt ſhe flattered herſelf with this Imagination, ſhe began to find an Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him, and judging the Opportunity
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33136:32"/> favourable, to ſhew Pity, as well as to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie her own Appetite; One night, as he was called to take the Lights, to carry them before her to her own Apartment, from her Lords, ſhe took occaſion to ſend away her other Attendants, in ſome Imployments ſhe found for them; when he had ſet down the Candles, ſays ſhe with a pleaſant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and with a Look that might encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the moſt timorous Lover; <hi>Cornelius,</hi> I cannot put it out of my thoughts, that I have ſeen you ſomewhere, before you came into my ſervice; pray tell me, if I did, on what occaſion it was? the young man ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, between Joy and Fear, at that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Queſtion, immediately falling on his Knees, ſaid; Madam, you have ſeen me, but if I tell you the occaſion, perhaps you will turn me out of your Service, and then I am undone for ever; I am ſure it will coſt me my little Wits, if not my Life; for in the Condition I am now, I know not what I do, when I am out of your ſight, and am once a day, in the mind to hang my ſelf, but when I think I ſhall never ſee you afterwards, I cannot find in my heart to do it. This fooliſh way of expreſſing himſelf, made her loſe the Opinion ſhe had conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his Quality but increaſed her Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to know what he was, and what he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33136:32"/> meant, and then looking ſternly on him, ſhe ſaid, I muſt know what and from whence you are, or elſe I ſhall certainly turn you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to morrow; ſhe heard her Women coming, and therefore commanded him to riſe, and reſolve to ſatisfie her the next Morning, when ſhe ſhould ſend for him, and ſo diſmiſt him, to haſten <hi>Philaenis</hi> to her, who met her coming into the Chamber as he went out. The next Morning, <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> who, though ſhe had ſometime after ſhe went to bed, ruminated on the Anſwer <hi>Cornelius</hi> mader her, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manner of his expreſſing himſelf, could not unriddle the meaning of it; as ſoon as ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was up, ſent for him, and diſmiſſing her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttendants, till ſhe ſhould ſend for them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid to him, you muſt now give me a true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccount of what I demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of you laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght, or I ſhall immediately cauſe you to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſmiſſed, with Directions, that if afterw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds you are ſeen about my Houſe, you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be driven away with Cudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. Madam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays he, falling on his Knees, if you will pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>don me the Fault you make me confeſs, I will tell you all the Truth. I do pardon y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſays ſhe, whatever it be, on condition y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u hide nothing from me, and if any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther be concerned with you, you diſcove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them likewiſe. Madam, ſays he, the Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce is all my own, nor does any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33136:33"/> one in the World, but your Ladiſhip and <hi>Philaenis</hi> know any thing of it. About two months ſince I was a Servant to <hi>Melon,</hi> that keeps the great Gardens near the old Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, where attending one morning early, to deliver out Fruits to the Huckſters, who came to buy, there came into the Garden two young Women, dreſt in the Habits of thoſe Fruit-ſellers, that go about among Perſons of Quality, but who were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dreſt, and a thouſand times handſomer, than any that ever I ſaw there before on that buſineſs; it was my Fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to attend them, and to gather what they call'd for; whilſt I was at work, they askt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo many pretty Queſtions, and then talked to one another about ſomething I did not underſtand, but which I perceived made th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m very merry, that I could not but take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otice of them, eſpecially of one who ſeeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Woman, on whom I had no ſooner fixt my Eye, but I found ſometh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng ſtick to my heart; when I had delivered t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em the Fruit, I could not forbear to venture to kiſs the Perſon I liked ſo well, though ſhe refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d me with a great deal of anger. Whilſt we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere ſtrugling, a Gentleman came towards us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hreatning me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for my Rudeneſs; I withdr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w haſtily, to decline hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fury, and getting b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ind a Hedg, I obſerved him to joyn the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Women,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33136:33"/> and then ſeparating her that I had ingaged with, they walked into a Wilderneſs, I durſt not go too near, to diſcover what they did, and to overhear what they ſaid; for beſides that, I was really afraid of the Gentleman, the other Woman kept that diſtance from them, that no body could come near enough to obſerve them, without being firſt diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I watcht notwithſtanding till they went out of the Garden, and at a diſtance followed till I ſaw the Gentleman put the two Women into your Ladiſhips Vineyard. All the day-after, and for ſeveral others, I could do nothing but think of thoſe two Women, and caſt about, how I might know who they were; I concluded they were ſome of the Maids of your Family, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to meet this Gentleman, yet I could not reſt, till I ſaw them again; I took all occaſions to be about your houſe, to obſerve all that went in and out, to ſeek pretences to come to the Laundry and other Offices of your Family, but could not ſet eye on the Perſon I lookt for, till one day thus, as I was ſtanding in the Court, your Ladiſhip came out to take Coach, talking pleaſantly with Madam <hi>Philaenis,</hi> by the ſound of your Voice and the air of your Face, I was inſtantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that you were the Lady I had been ſo rude to, which ſtruck ſuch a Terrour into
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33136:34"/> me, that as ſoon as your Chariot was gone, and I could not ſee it any longer, I came home to my Maſter, fearing that if you had taken notice of me, I ſhould have been pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for my ſawcineſs, as I deſerved; but I found it was in vain to keep from you, my mind was ſo imployed in the thoughts of what I had done, and to whom, that I could not follow my work as I was uſed to do, many Rebukes and ſome Blows I received from my Maſter, and in five days, was turned out of my Service, as being become Fool or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. It was then much worſe with me, and I had not wherewithal to maintain my ſelf, and found no inclination to go to labour, but hanging about this Houſe, not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be from it, nor knowing why I ſtaid here, I happened among your Ladiſhips Footmen, who were making a Running Match between two of them that diſputed which had the beſt heel; when they ran, I ſtarted with them, and being uſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant labour, and ſo better winded, I beat them both, by which I gained credit amongſt them, that in few days I was offered your Ladiſhips Livery; ſince then, your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip knows the diligence I have uſed in my Waiting. Well, ſays <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed you my Pardon, and I muſt keep my Word; but take care you carry your ſelf ſo,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33136:34"/> that no one in the World may perceive by your Carriage or Language that you Love, or at leaſt who it is you Love; with that ſhe bid him call her Women, and that Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told <hi>Philaenis,</hi> ſhe heard the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a Noiſe at the Door of the Anti-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber towards the Terrace; ſhe did not know what it meant, and therefore would have her order <hi>Cornelius</hi> to bring his Bed into that Room after ſhe was abed, and lye there. She made her at that time no further Privy to her Deſign, nor did <hi>Philaenis</hi> make any Reflection upon it, but purſued her Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that night, after all were gone to their reſt, and <hi>Nicerotis</hi> obſerved by the ſilence of the Night, that her Man was ſetled in his Bed; ſhe called with a loud Voice, <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Cornelius,</hi> at which he riſing, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Door of his Ladies Chamber, and going to the Bed-ſide, Madam, ſaid he, did you call? I ſays ſhe, in ſome diſorder; did you hear no Noiſe? none ſays he, but your call. I called you, ſays ſhe, becauſe I heard ſome noiſe at the Terrace Door; I'le go and ſee, ſays he, if any one be there, no, ſays ſhe, perhaps it be ſome Spirits that are about, then I'le hide my ſelf in my Bed, ſays he, for I am afraid of Spirits of all things in the World; than you'l leave me to be frighted; you muſt hide your ſelf here, ſays ſhe: with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33136:35"/> that, in a great Fright, and not knowing what he did, he got <gap reason="omitted: lacuna" resp="#SOURCE"/> Two or three days after, <hi>Cornelius</hi> being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verjoyed, could not hold, he muſt needs give vent to his thoughts, which were too full of his undeſerved happineſs, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned in the breſt of a wiſer Man he took one of his Fellows aſide, with whom he had moſt familiarity, and told him how good an Office he was preferred to, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing placed to keep the Spirits from his Lady in the night, now ſhe lay alone. I do not envy you that Imployme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ſays <hi>Pardelis,</hi> I had rather ſleep at night, and not dream of the Devil; beſides, are you not afraid of Spirits? I was extreamly, when ſhe told me firſt what I was to do, and was running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to hide my ſelf under my Bed-Cloaths, ſays <hi>Cornelius,</hi> but ſhe call'd me Fool, and told me, ſhe would keep the Spirits from me then, and bid me hide my ſelf in her Bed-Cloaths; <hi>Pardelis,</hi> who deſigned a further Explication, was call'd away, and could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover no further at that time; but he had learnt enough, and being one that was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Family by <hi>Zeniſces,</hi> a malicious Lord, who having ſomething of Confidence with <hi>Leontius,</hi> and thereby a Knowledge of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33136:35"/> 
                  <hi>Nicerotis</hi> her temper, had made ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuccesful Addreſſes, and therefore was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to diſcover her Intrigues, which he was aſſured ſhe could not live without. His Spy, ſoon gave him an Account of this Paſſage, and his Curioſity preſſed him to pry farther into the Affair. He ordered <hi>Pardelis</hi> to get his Lord or Ladies Maſter-Key, that opened all the Locks of the Houſe and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and to bring it to him as ſoon as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could, and it was not difficult for him to do ſo: For during <hi>Nicias</hi> his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his Key had lain on his twi-light, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded of any, which he conveyed the next day to <hi>Zeniſces;</hi> the next night he entred the Garden, and came to the Terrace, where he obſerved <hi>Cornelius</hi> bringing in his Bed and laying down, and ſoon after, riſing in his Shirt, and going into his Ladies Chamber; after a very little pauſe, he ſoftly opens the Terrace Door, and comes ſoftly into the Chamber to the Bed-ſide, and opening a Dark-Lanthorn which he had in one hand, with the other opens the Curtains, and views the kind Couple in their Embraces; he made a terrible roaring Noiſe, the Lady ſhriekt, and the Footman frighted at the Noiſe and flaſh of the Light, as if the Devil were come to take him in the Fact, ſwound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away; <hi>Zeniſces</hi> retired immediately, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33136:36"/> locking the Door after him, went off, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly laughing to himſelf at the prank he had plaid, and ſtudying how to improve it, to be revenged for the Neglects and Slights he had received. The noiſe wakned <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenis,</hi> whoſe Chamber was next her Ladies; ſhe ran in to ſee what was the Matter, and there found her in her Smock, riſen out of her Bed, and pulling the Footman by the Noſe, to bring him to Life. O Madam! ſays ſhe, what is the Matter? Ask me no Queſtions, ſays ſhe, but help to pull this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low away, and carry him to his Bed, the Houſe will be all up preſently, and I ſhall be undone; they pull'd him out by the Hair and the Noſe, the violence and falling on the Ground, brought him to himſelf, and they thruſt him out into his own Bed, and bid him lie ſtill, as if he were yet in a Swound, what ever happened. By this time ſeveral of the Family were raiſed, and ſome running where the Noiſe was heard (for the Lady and <hi>Philenis</hi> both call'd out as loud as they could) found them in great diſorder, complaining of a ſtrange Apparition, which had put them into a terrible Fright; they went to pull up <hi>Cornelius,</hi> but he holding the Cloaths faſt about him, cryed, good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil let me alone, do not take me, take my Lady. Which ſhe hearing, and fearing the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33136:36"/> Fool might make ſome Confeſſion, bid the Company withdraw, and that <hi>Philaenis</hi> ſhould come to Bed to her; ſhe bid them ſee if the Terrace Doors were lockt, and make no more noiſe in the Houſe. <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> hearing theſe Orders, got up, dreſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and went away to his Fellows Lodgings, and <hi>Pardelis</hi> ſet up the reſt of the night to ſecure the frighted Lady, who knew the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Devil too well, to be afraid of him; the next morning, the Houſe was all in an Uproar; the old Lady <hi>Sophonia</hi> was much ſcandalized, at her Daughters appointing the Footman to lye in her Anti-Chamber and ſuſpected there was ſome unhandſome Prank plaid, that would be diſcovered, to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of her Family. She ſpake to <hi>Nicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> with ſome ſevere Reflections upon her Conduct, which coming from a Mother-in-Law, galled ſo cruelly, that afterwards ſhe could not endure the gentleſt Advice from her. All that were of any Diſcretion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to conceal this from <hi>Nicias;</hi> but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew days there wanted not ſome impertine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Viſiter, that would needs be ſatisfied by him, of the truth of this Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition, that was ſo much talkt of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Town, to have frighted his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: this bred a new Diſturbance, and upon his enquiry, the Story being told him, as it
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33136:37"/> ſeemed to them who knew well the whole truth (which few did) he fell into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant paſſion, being a man of a Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick temper, and one that had known the World enough, and he had broken out into ſome Outrages, but that his Ladies Quality, and the Conſideration of her Relations, cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him into thoughts more becoming his Condition; he immediately directed that <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſhould be diſcharged the Family, and commanded privately to withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the City, with Threats, that if he appeared there, he would give order to have him ſold for a Slave to the <hi>Sarazens;</hi> this quieted the Family; but <hi>Zeniſces</hi> had made ſo many Confidents of this Adventure of his, in the Diſguiſe of a Spirit, though to moſt of them, he related it under feigned Names, that ſome Poetaſter among them, made a Ballad of it, which was ſung up and down the Streets, by all the Boys of the Town.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though <hi>Phillis</hi> be Coy, ſhe's not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> laſt,</l>
                     <l>She's demure all day, yet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ight,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe has not a Man by the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt,</l>
                     <l>She's in a pitiful Fright.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:33136:37"/>
                     <l>Her Footman ſhe call'd to her Bed,</l>
                     <l>To keep the foul Devil away;</l>
                     <l>But he ſwore it ſhould not be ſaid,</l>
                     <l>He tempted her to ſuch foul Play.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He appeared with terrible Look,</l>
                     <l>And told her ſhe was to blame,</l>
                     <l>Thus to ſlight all the Care he took,</l>
                     <l>To breed her for Nobler Game.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>By this time <hi>Ariſtander</hi> was ſo recovered, that he went abroad; his firſt Viſits were to his Friend <hi>Nicias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Adventure of <hi>Nicerotis</hi> (as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hinted) was only a Fiction, invented by the witty Malice of a certain Perſon, that had prov'd unſucceſsful in attempting that Kindneſs from her, whereof he thought ſome others were poſſeſt. And indeed the Story was contriv'd with ſo much Art and Humor, that it was preſently taken up by the Poetaſter of the Times; but by reaſon that the firſt inventer of the Tale, reported it under borrowed Names, there was none of them that knew upon what Perſon to faſten, ſo that her own Friends and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons never ſuſpected her to be concern'd in it. One of theſe Eſſays being of a particular Humour from all the reſt, and in Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33136:38"/> of the Lady, as if the Paſſages had been really true, we have thought fit to inſert it. The Lines were theſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>In vain you little Scriblers of the Times,</l>
                  <l>Conſpire to blaſt the Fair with envious Rhimes;</l>
                  <l>In vain your feeble Satyr is apply'd,</l>
                  <l>For Wit is always found on Beauties ſide.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>(Phillis)</hi> none thy Conduct diſapprove,</l>
                  <l>What's Birth or Title in Affairs of Love:</l>
                  <l>Where-ere this Monarch lets his Favour fall,</l>
                  <l>It ſtreight gives Honour and ennobles all.</l>
                  <l>When Sov'raign Beauty pleaſes to be kind,</l>
                  <l>It makes the Merit which it does not find:</l>
                  <l>Without diſtinction, fragrant Showers diſtil,</l>
                  <l>The Sun ſalutes the Valley with the Hill.</l>
                  <l>Beſtows on all his Light and genial Flame;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not brighter Beauty do the ſame?</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Phillis,</hi> take your juſt Prerogative,</l>
                  <l>To Slaves and Princes, equal Favours give;</l>
                  <l>While none ſhall dare to call your Conduct light,</l>
                  <l>Such Wit and Beauty muſt be in the Right.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This Apology was lookt upon as tolerable enough, and the ſevereſt Criticks cou'd
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33136:38"/> not but allow ſome, to ſo generous an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker.</p>
               <p>In the mean while <hi>Nicias</hi> was ſo well recovered of his Wounds, that he had been abroad, and more than once made Viſits to his Friend <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> The Intimacy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them was ſo great, that their being together, though never ſo frequently, cou'd ſeem no wonder; yet <hi>Nicias,</hi> in his latter Conferences, expreſt more Importunacy of Affection, than had been obſerv'd by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander</hi> in his former Friendſhip. Some weighty Concern ſeem'd to be working in his thoughts, which he appear'd deſirous to have communicated to his Friend, and thought fitting to uſher in that Truſt he meant to repoſe in him, with new and more than common Endearments. <hi>Ariſtander</hi> however was yet in the dark, as to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and <hi>Nicias</hi> concluded within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that the propereſt Advance, would be by firſt breaking his Deſign to <hi>Nicerotis;</hi> to whom, in private, with an unuſual Zeal, he continually extolls the Merits of his Friend <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> She was for ſome time at a loſs, concerning his Intention herein, not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it poſſible that a Perſon of his Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo nice in his Honour, and ſenſible of his Ladies extraordinary Beauty, could ever in the leaſt ſollicite her, to confer the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33136:39"/> of ſuch Sweets on any but himſelf. She wanted not various Reflections hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he hereby made but an Eſſay of her Virtue, yet the Importunity with which he preſt her, convinc'd her at laſt that he was in earneſt. <hi>Ariſtander</hi> was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Accompliſhments, that might charm a Lady of more reſervedneſs than <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> Yet this Sollici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation coming from her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, provokt her to extream Rage, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever her own Inclination might have been; yet this Entreaty ſeeming to expreſs in him leſs eſteem of the Beauty he enjoy'd, than it deſerv'd, made his demand moſt diſpleaſing to her; inſomuch that out of Revenge of his Contempt (as ſhe judg'd it) and the eaſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Temper, as Love was no hard Task to her, ſhe really admits a Paſſion for <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> In order to this Affair, ſhe contracts an intimate Acquaintance with his Wife <hi>Eubea,</hi> a Lady of ſuch Sincerity and Innocence in her ſelf, and ſo free from Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of others, with many more ſuch good Diſpoſitions, as every way qualified her for a Friend.</p>
               <p>One Afternoon, in the freedom of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, amongſt other Arguments, they ſpent ſome Talk on the Nature and Effects of Love; which of all Paſſions, had this Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity particular to it ſelf, that it was of no
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33136:39"/> leſs difficulty to create it where it was not, than to extinguiſh it where it had once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fire. Several Tragical Inſtances of the former were repeated by <hi>Eubea;</hi> in the Concluſion whereof, <hi>Nicerotis</hi> burſting forth into Tears, cries out, Let the Misfortunes of Antiquity ſleep in ſilence; our own Age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds too much with ſad Examples of this nature, and amongſt them all none more wretched than <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> I know not (ſaid ſhe) whether the Privation of Happineſs, ought really to be accounted miſery, but what ſhall we ſay, when the Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that is attended with the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable and incurable Evils? ſuch, my <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bea,</hi> is the ſtate of diſappointed Love; where the Unhappy are not only deprived of that Paradiſe which was preſented to their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and left to their primitive free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but with the utmoſt ſeverity of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, condemn'd to loath'd Embraces. It is not enough for the rendring of a Conjugal State happy, that the Perſon to whom we give our Vows, has all the Endowments of Art and Nature to make him amiable, unleſs our Breaſts are diſengag'd from any other Paſſion, for that will be ſure to maintain the Fort againſt the braveſt Aſſailants, and in ſpight of all Attempts that our Prudence can make, to ſuppreſs the Remembrance of it,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33136:40"/> will often return upon us, to the Diſturbance of our Quiet.</p>
               <p>It cannot be deny'd, that the Birth and Education, the many natural and acquired Excellencies of the Lord <hi>Nicias,</hi> were ſuch, as wou'd have bleſt any Breaſt but mine, and that I perhaps was the only perſon, whom ſo accompliſht a Man cou'd have made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy. Take my <hi>Eubea,</hi> this Confeſſion, for the greateſt Inſtance of Friendſhip to your ſelf, as it is the Argument of greateſt ſorrow to me. <hi>Nicias,</hi> though deſtin'd for my Husband, came yet too late for a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. My Heart had been before, without the leaſt reſerve, diſpos'd off to young <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthus,</hi> nor was my Conqueſt over his, leſs entire. It was the firſt time that either of us had been ſenſible of Love; and as firſt Deſires are generally moſt violent, I am confident that no Tranſports ever equall'd ours. Beſides the Advantages of his Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the ſingular Charms of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which ſate upon him without the leaſt Affectation, ſuch was the agreeableneſs of his Converſation, and every way ſo ſuited to my Inclination, that I could not perſwade my ſelf, but that we were born for each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers happineſs. It is impoſſible to expreſs the Satisfaction we took in each others Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and though our Opportunities of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33136:40"/> meeting were frequent, yet every parting was with ſuch regret, that we even envy'd our ſelves thoſe delightful Minutes, we were before ſo impatient to be poſſeſt of. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was now wanting to compleat our Joy, but the Conſent of our Friends, which we had no reaſon to deſpair of; for beſide the Equality of our Fortune, it had been an eternal Tye of the Amity that had long been between the two Families. And indeed the Prudence, as well as the Kindneſs of our Parents was herein exerted, in that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd as much as they cou'd, their deſigning a Match between us, to make it ſeem as much as cou'd be, the effect of our own Choice and free Inclination, which was likely to have made it much more eaſie to us, than if it had ſeemed of their impoſing. <hi>Philanthus</hi> was now taking reſolution to acquaint his Parents with his Paſſion, when the ſafety of the Publick was threatned, by a moſt ſuddain and unexpected Diſturbance from the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> who came with all their Naval Force to ſurprize us in our Security, as depending upon the late Peace that was ſolemnly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded on between us. <hi>Philanthus</hi> was now of thoſe years, in which ſeveral of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had ſignaliz'd their Courage; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom, none was ever abſent from the Service of his Country in any publick
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33136:41"/> Action; nor could he be prevail'd with, to degenerate from their Example on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. To which, notwithſtanding all the Cautions that a tender Miſtreſs cou'd repeat to a Lover, whom Youth and Ambition might betray to utmoſt danger, I parted from him with all the Violence of a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Sorrow, while he was poſſeſt with no leſs confidence of Succeſs. Our Reſidence was on the Borders of the Sea, and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the Fleets not many Leagues from the Coaſt. The Diſpute continued for almoſt three days, two whereof were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd by me, in watching from the Clifts, where he and I had been wont to view the Sea, and enjoy the Calmneſs of the Ev'nings. On the third Morning, I cou'd perceive the Fleets make further and further off to Sea, by which I knew our Ships had the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> upon the Chace. This was the firſt time I could endure to withdraw my Eyes from them, when caſting them down to the Foot of the Rock, I was ſaluted with the moſt lamentable Object that ever wretched Maid beheld; the Body of my Lover brought in a Boat to the Shore. Think my <hi>Eubea,</hi> if poſſible, what Agonies that Spectacle muſt have ſtruck me with, and what Effects it was likely to produce. Spare, ſpare me the Remembrance of thoſe ſorrowful Hours
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33136:41"/> that enſu'd, and the mournful Reflections of my Deſpair, upon the happy Minutes we had paſs'd together; the thouſand endearing Words with which he uſed to charm my Soul into his Breaſt; which now, all forſaken and diſconſolate, I in vain repeated to the Rocks and Shades, where we were wont to converſe. It was no wonder, if now I grew indifferent, which way I was diſpoſed on for the future, and unconcern'd, to whoſe ſhare this little Beauty fell, when <hi>Philanthus</hi> was cut off from poſſeſſing it. It was at this time, that <hi>Nicias</hi> made his Application, and preſt for Marriage with me, which I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, being tired with the Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my Parents, who preſum'd it the beſt expedient that could be, to bring forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of what had happen'd. I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that <hi>Nicias,</hi> his Paſſion for me, was for a long time what he pretended, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I apply'd my ſelf to make him all poſſible Returns of Duty, which even the Eyes of Jealouſie and Envy cou'd never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh from the ſincerity of Affection, which in time became indeed advanc'd to that degree of Kindneſs, that few Wives are poſſeſt with, for the Huſbands of their own chooſing. It was at this unſeaſonable time that <hi>Nicias</hi> began to take a Surfeit of his Happineſs, when indeed, I ought to have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33136:42"/> been more dear to him than ever; but ſuch is the Choice or Fate of Mankind, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue with eagerneſs thoſe Bleſſings that ſhun them, and to fly from them that purſue. I could perceive by many Inſtances, the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indifferency of his Carriage towards me, nor was it long, before I underſtood that <hi>Thalaſſa's</hi> Charms had occaſion'd this Change; and if any thing could have been an excuſe for broken Faith, her extraordinary Beauty would even have juſtified the Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. He took all poſſible occaſions of making her acquainted with his Paſſion, and at laſt became ſo importunate with her, that in her own Defence (being a Lady of ſtrict Virtue) ſhe was forc'd to acquaint me <hi>Nicias</hi> his Addreſſes to her, and askt my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, what courſe to take for my Intereſt, and her own Quiet. Notwithſtanding my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation at the hearing of this, I returned her my thanks, and told her, that to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Obligation, ſhe muſt feign a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with <hi>Nicias,</hi> when he next came to ſollicite her, and to make him an Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at ſuch time and Place, that I might, unknown to him, ſupply her Room. This was ſeveral times performed by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing of my Voice, and the Darkneſs of the Apartments. With what Tranſport did he meet thoſe Embraces, for which he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33136:42"/> ſhew'd ſo much Indifference at home? Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Thalaſſa,</hi> ſaid he, I was never acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Bliſs till this Minute; dull miſtaken <hi>Nicias,</hi> that cou'd ever imagine that he taſted Delight in the Arms of <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> I was before ſcarce able to contain with Rage, and now with Laughter. At our parting he immediately went towards home, yet not ſo ſoon but that I made a ſhift to reach the Houſe, and beſtow my ſelf on a Couch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he arriv'd at his entring of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. You muſt imagine (continued ſhe) what Sentiments this Diſcovery poſſeſt me with, and my uneaſineſs was the greater, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had as yet reſerved the Trouble within my own Thoughts, nor ſo much as once in expreſs Words, let <hi>Nicias</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I was ſenſible of his Falſhood; it is therefore no wonder, if at this time, my Friends obſerv'd in me an unuſual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedneſs and Melancholy. All this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was delivered by <hi>Nicerotis</hi> with ſo much tenderneſs, that <hi>Eubea</hi> was extreamly toucht, having a Heart and Temper apt for all thoſe Impreſſions that are felt in a Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Friendſhip, which ſhe poſſeſt in the higheſt degree for <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> However, ſhe thought that condoling with her on this Argument, might only give her a greater ſenſe of her Misfortune; ſhe therefore judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33136:43"/> it more prudent to pacifie her what ſhe cou'd, and above all things counſelled her, to ſuffer nothing to be occaſion of breach between her Husband and her. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſuch was the ſingular goodneſs of her Temper, that ſhe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a conſtant Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, when any Diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rence happen'd between them. Being therefore poſſeſt with ſo great a Kindneſs for <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> and ſo high an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of her Virtue, it is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, that ſhe had not the leaſt Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the Inclination ſhe had entertained for <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> and of which he was now ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by ſeveral Inſtances. It was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the ſtricteſt Virtue to be inſenſible of <hi>Nicerotis</hi> Charms; yet there were ſo many complicated Reaſons againſt his indulging any ſuch Thought (and chiefly, his Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with <hi>Nicias</hi>) that he was reſolved to purſue no Advantage that might offer it ſelf, but to ſhun all Occaſions that might lead thereunto. <hi>Nicias</hi> (as was before hinted) had in later Conferences with him, expreſſed more importunate Friendſhip than formerly, as it were, to prepare for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Truſt that he intended to repoſe in him, though as yet he had not expreſly communicated it to him. However, he was ſo far proceeded in it, that he had already engaged <hi>Ariſtander</hi> in the whole care of his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33136:43"/> Affairs, which he at firſt ſcrupled, not as being an act of Friendſhip, and for ſeveral ſpecious Reaſons which <hi>Nicias</hi> gave him for ſo doing: Yet finding after a little Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that it might miniſter opportunities of any Amour with <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> or occaſion any Difference between himſelf and <hi>Eubea,</hi> he wholly declined the Management of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> his Concerns, on Pretences plauſible enough, without informing him of the true Cauſe. This Ceſſation notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was but of ſhort continuance; for <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> his ill Adventures in the Duel, together with private Diſcontents, and other Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, reduced him to ſuch Indiſpoſition of Body, that to recover his Health, it was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for him to leave that Country, and remove to a more agreeable Climate. So that now in the height of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtanders</hi> ſatisfaction, which he took in hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo handſomely diſengaged himſelf from the Management of his Friends Concerns, without diſobliging him in the refuſal, whereby he thought himſelf free from all occaſion and temptation towards any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue with <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> which for the Reaſons we have expreſt, he was reſolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline; at the very time (I ſay) that he was moſt pleaſing himſelf with theſe Reflections, he was unexpectedly acquainted with the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33136:44"/> News of <hi>Nicias</hi>'s ſudden departure from that Place, and could by no means believe it, till he was confirmed of it by this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, directed to himſelf.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>MY Departure to another Countrey, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Leave taken of ſo dear a Friend as <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> muſt poſſeſs him with no little Surprize; But by all the ſincerity of our Friendſhip, I conjure you not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſs, which is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of Diſcontent: I leave your ſelf to judge how afflicting that trouble muſt be, which I would make any ſcruple of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating to <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> The Griefs with which I labour, would extort Pity from an Enemy; what influence then would they have upon you? no, my Friend, I will be more tender of your Quiet, then to wound you with the Knowledge of them; and thus far acquaint you with them, only to engage you to the performance of what I have to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. My VVife and my whole Concerns I leave to your care; I am ſenſible of the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then I lay upon you, but to accept of trouble, is the Office of a Friend, ſuch I have found you in the highest Degree, and know, that beſide the Conſideration of Friendſhip, you undetake here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Kindneſs to the Miſerable.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:33136:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtander</hi> read over theſe Lines ſeveral times, and ſtill found himſelf more and more aſtoniſht with the Contents. The Diſorder in the Expreſſion, and the matter they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, ſufficiently confirm'd him, how great Trouble and Difficulty his Friend labour'd under, at the writing of them, and was not a little afflicted, that he was in no poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (by reaſon of his Abſence) of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſuch Counſel or Relief, as his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might inſpire him with, on ſuch an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. But having ſufficiently condoled within himſelf the Miſeries with which <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> was oppreſt, he perceiv'd himſelf again inevitably involv'd in the Management of his Concerns, and conſequently the ſame Inconveniencies and Apprehenſions return'd upon him, for which he ſo induſtriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd that Office before. His doubts and perplexity hereupon were ſo great, that his Uneaſineſs was preſently obſerv'd by <hi>Eubea,</hi> who extreamly preſt him to diſcover the Cauſe. All the Account that he gave her, was his Sorrow for his Friends ſo ſudden Removal, and the Unſetled Poſture in which he had left his Affairs. I condole (reply'd <hi>Eubea</hi>) as much as poſſibly you can do, any Misfortune of the Lord <hi>Nicias,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I ſhould very ill deſerve that Degree of Friendſhip, which I am favour'd with by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33136:45"/> 
                  <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> The ſmalleſt Concern of his, whilſt out of his own Power ought to be of great importance to you, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his deareſt part, the deſtitute <hi>Nicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> muſt be your principal Care. Let me therefore conjure you, as I have any ſhare in your Affection, to contribute all that poſſibly you can to the diverting of her Grief, and making her Trouble ſit eaſie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her. Theſe Arguments, and whatever elſe could poſſibly be inſiſted on by <hi>Eubea,</hi> in behalf of her Friend <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> were urged by her with all the earneſtneſs that could be. <hi>Ariſtander</hi> notwithſtanding made her no ſudden Anſwer, being wholly taken up with contemplation on this Adventure, and yet could not but ſmile ſecretly at <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bea's</hi> preſſing Sollicitation, being conſcious to himſelf, that his Averſion to engage in <hi>Nicerotis</hi> Affairs, was not out of any want of kindneſs to her, but meerly a Principle of juſtice, and moſt eſpecially towards <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bea.</hi> He was now ſenſible by many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that an Addreſs from him to <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> was likely to meet with ſmall Oppoſition; nor was he willing to venture on ſuch Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of making Advances that way, as the whole Management of her Concerns muſt needs offer to him.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33136:45"/>
               <p>And though an Attempt of that kind might ſeem inconſiſtent with a generous Nature in any Circumſtances, yet the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſtreſs which his Friend lay under, and the Confidence he had repoſed in him at this time, made every thought that might have a tendency that way, with the utmoſt Reſolution rejected by him. However, <hi>Eubea</hi> was ſo reſtleſs in her Entreaties, and the diſconſolate Condition of his Friend were ſo prevailing, that he could not but comply with his Deſire, in eſpouſing intirely the Care of his Wife and Fortunes, and by this means, to be under neceſſity of frequent Converſation with <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> She was not diſpleaſed herewith, nor was it leſs to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eubea,</hi> who was never better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, than when <hi>Nicerotis</hi> and <hi>Ariſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> were in Company with each other.</p>
               <p>Some conſiderable time paſſed over in this manner, while <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> with all the ſincerity of a faithful Friend, and with much induſtry, performed the Charge that was left upon him. <hi>Eubea</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill without the leaſt Jealouſie, and infinitely pleaſed, to find the Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in her Husband, diſcharged with ſo much advantage to <hi>Nicerotis. Nicias,</hi> in the mean time, after much weakneſs, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33136:46"/> increaſe of his Indiſpoſition, was at laſt recovered to that ſeeming degree of health, as to think of adventuring back again to his own Country, where he found, upon all Accounts, the good effects of his Friends careful Management; nor was <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander</hi> leſs pleaſed at having had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of being ſerviceable to him at a time of diſtreſs: but withal, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations we have expreſt, was well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough contented to be diſengaged from his Imployment, and to reſign his Office into <hi>Nicias</hi> his own Hands. <hi>Nicias</hi> could not but accept of the Surrender, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing now in a Condition to excuſe his F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nd from the trouble; yet <hi>Ariſtander</hi> perceived a ſecret reluctancy in him, on the removal of his Affairs out of his hands, and ſeemed inclinable, that not only his Fortunes but his Wife ſhould ſtill be under <hi>Aristanders</hi> Care. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, not being very expreſs therein at that time, <hi>Ariſtander</hi> once more, thought himſelf totally exempted from that Office, and from danger or inconvenience that might occur thereby. This Reſpite again was but of ſhort Continuance, for <hi>Nicias</hi> relapſing into a worſe Condition than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, once more entreats his Friends Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Conduct in his Buſineſs,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33136:46"/> which was accepted as formerly by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander.</hi> After this re-engagement, <hi>Nicias</hi> ſeemed every day increaſe in his Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Amity towards his Friend; but ſtill labouring with ſome ſecret, which he was reſtleſs to communicate unto him. One Evening, being ſomething more than ordinary refreſht in his Spirits, when none were preſent beſides his Wife and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander,</hi> after ſilence for ſome minutes, with a Smile, he uttered theſe Words. The Love (ſaid he) of Parents to their own Off-ſpring is the practice of all the World, and has been ſo in all Ages; yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but reflect with ſome wonder, how a Cuſtom ſhould prevail ſo upon all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, without any one rational Cauſe to enforce it. The oddneſs of this Aſſertion, and the abrupt manner of his introducing it, put <hi>Nicerotis</hi> and <hi>Ariſtander</hi> into a pauſe, till <hi>Ariſtander</hi> made this Reply. It ſhould (ſaid he) rather be a Wonder (as the greateſt Crime againſt nature and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation from common ſenſe) to find that Parent, that were void of Love towards his own Iſſue. I grant you (proceeded <hi>Nicias</hi>) that a Deſcent of kindneſs to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity is moſt natural; but from whence that Diſtinction ſhould proceed, the great difference of Affection between the Off-ſpring
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33136:47"/> of our own Bodies, and other mens, eſpecially of Kindred and Friends, is to me, altogether unaccountable; for it is plain (continued he) that it is not the perſonal Merit, the intrinſick Virtues and Qualifications which our Children may happen to be endowed with, that engages our Love towards them; for we often find them far excelled upon theſe accounts, by the Off-ſpring of others, for whom, yet we are poſſeſt with no ſuch fondneſs, and what other Conſideration ſhould lead a reaſonable man to ſuch partiality, is paſt my underſtanding. You will not certainly (ſaid <hi>Nicerotis</hi>) diſpute the Prudence of a Practice which nature (that is the ſupream eternal Reaſon) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires; beſides, if it were not the Effect of an Inſtinct that reigns through the whole Creation, yet what can be more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to common Equity, than for Parents to have particular care and indulgence for thoſe Perſons, of whoſe Beings (next to Providence) they were the immediate Authors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To ſay nothing of theſe duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which ought, and for the moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt are paid by Children to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, there is yet methinks (replies <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi>) a poorneſs of Spirit, and ſomething of a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>id ſelfiſhneſs, in fondneſs of our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33136:47"/> own Products, more than thoſe of a Friend. It is evidently the nature of friendſhip, in perfection, to hold our friend in equal value with our ſelves, nay, even to ſubmit our own Intereſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to his; if therefore my Friend appear to me of ſuch merit, as to claim Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from me, equal to what I have for my ſelf, I know not why I ſhould not be as fond of his Likeneſs as my own. Why ſhould not the ſame reaſoning hold in the Copy, as in the Original? And why the Son of that Perſon whom I hold dearer than my ſelf, ſhould not be dearer to me, than one that ſprung from my ſelf, I cannot comprehend? and that my Friendſhip for <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> is elevated to that Degree I muſt needs acknowledge. Theſe laſt Expreſſions of <hi>Nicias,</hi> put <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtander</hi> and <hi>Nicerotis</hi> to the Bluſh, who knew not how to reply on this occaſion; for they could not take notice of the Conſequence that muſt neceſſarily follow, from what <hi>Nicias</hi> had ſaid. He plainly expreſt it his judgment, that the Child of a Friend, ſhould be dearer to him than his own, and that <hi>Ariſtander</hi> was that Friend, and they were alſo ſenſible, that towards ſuch a Birth, he included his own Wife. The Right of a Huſband (proceeded he) in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33136:48"/> his own Wife, is indiſputable, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is the fouleſt Violation of Juſtice, to invade any man in that Tenure; but Conſent removes all notion of Injury, and to ſay that a Man has not diſpoſal of that Poſſeſſion, as he ſhall think fit, is to ſay, he has leſs Right in his Wife, than in his meaneſt Chattels; if therefore a Huſband, by any Misfortune or Irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſhould think himſelf uncapable of Off-ſpring in his own Perſon, I know not why the Wife ſhould therefore be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded from the comfort of Children. Therefore in ſuch Circumſtances (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where the having an Heir is requiſite) if by Conſent, the Friend ſupplies the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Huſband, it is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Injury, that it muſt be eſteemed an Obligation. Theſe Arguments were delivered by <hi>Nicias,</hi> with ſo firm a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſuch an earneſtneſs in his Eyes, as plainly diſcovered his Intention by this Diſcourſe, and that he deſired his Wife and <hi>Ariſtander</hi> to take it, with particular application to themſelves; and that the breaking this Deſign to them, was the Difficulty that had ſo long made him uneaſie, and towards which, he had ſo often made imperfect Attempts. Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore after this manner expreſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33136:48"/> himſelf (fixing his Looks moſt eagerly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them) he ſate expecting their Reply. But ſtill, the more plainly that his Drift was underſtood, the greater the Confuſion appeared in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicerotis</hi> was far from an Averſion to <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> and ſhe was by her Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no Enemy to Variety (beſides her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous enough of Children, and in no probability of having any by <hi>Nicias</hi>) yet, whether ſhe thought that this Propoſal of her Huſbands, ſavoured ſomething of Neglect towards her, though under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Juſtice to her, or whether ſhe thought her ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bliged in Modeſty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (at leaſt in appearance) ſo unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Charge, there was thereupon, a great Change of Colour, and Combat of Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in her Face. <hi>Aristander</hi> laboured with no leſs difficulty; for all the plauſible Reaſons that <hi>Nicias</hi> alledged, could not convince him, but that there was too much injuſtice in ſuch a Practice.</p>
               <p>The Conference was here broken off, by the approach of a Viſitant, who was not to be denied. It was the Lady <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riska,</hi> one that ſcorned to ſuffer time to have his uſual triumph over Perſons of her years, notwithſtanding which, ſhe ſtill retained all the Mirth and Gaity of her
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33136:49"/> youthful Humour. Her Inclination had always been for Company and Treats, and never ſo well ſatisfied as when ſhe ſaw the Affairs of Love going forward; if ſhe could therein make her Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſerviceable to a Friend, it was ſo much the more to her Content; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſee a fair Opportunity loſt, and ſtand out, when Action offered it ſelf, ſhe would not refuſe obliging a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. In the mean time, <hi>Ariſtander</hi> is wholly at a loſs, how to behave himſelf in this Adventure. And after through conſideration, once more reſolves upon wholly leaving <hi>Nicerotis</hi> Company, but is again prevented by the Sollicitations of his Wife. <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> however was reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not utterly to loſe the Advantage that offered it ſelf by this freedom. She therefore perceiving this Method ſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to her Huſband, contrives all Opportunities ſhe can of meeting with <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> Therefore as a fit Expedient herein, ſhe betakes her to <hi>Doriska</hi> for her aſſiſtance and direction, as it were to an Oracle, and the more, as knowing her to have ſome intimacy with <hi>Ariſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> The Matron return'd her many Complements, for the Opinion ſhe expreſt of her Judgment, and the Confidence ſhe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33136:49"/> was pleaſed to repoſe in her readineſs to ſerve her; and I hope (ſaid ſhe) I can give a more reaſonable account of my time and experience, than not to be able to direct any Friend that ſhall apply themſelves to me for Counſel in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of Love. <hi>Nicerotis</hi> ſmiled to her ſelf, and proceeded to ſay, it would be the moſt injurious thing in the World, not to allow her Ladiſhip an extrordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Talent in the Conduct of Amour. After this, ſhe freely imparted to her the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the late Diſcourſe that paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Nicias,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtander</hi> and her ſelf. The Matron again appeared extreamly ſatisfied with the Matter, with many poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Remarks upon it, but above all, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded the Sentiments and Reſolves of <hi>Nicias;</hi> and amongſt other things (ſaid ſhe) the wiſeſt Records of Antiquity will be found to be of his ſide. Let us go no farther for Inſtance, than the Confines of our own Country of <hi>Greece;</hi> what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth can boaſt of a Continuance like that of <hi>Lacedaemon?</hi> and what could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch duration, but the prudence and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of thoſe ſanctions that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the wiſe <hi>Lycurgus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch <hi>in</hi> Vitâ Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgi.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, I will be bold to affirm the great Latitude permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33136:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> to Wives in extraordinary Caſes, to have been of moſt important Advantage, where the Perſon ſubſtituted to him that was incapacitated, was not only reputed to perform a Kindneſs to his Friend, but likewiſe a moſt laudable Service to the State.</p>
               <p>This learned Diſcourſe of the old Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and the Zeal with which ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt her ſelf, gave no ſmall Diverſion to <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> Nor ſhe think bare Counſel ſufficient, for one that pretended friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, without ſhewing her ſelf active too in her Service. She therefore ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived Matters, that <hi>Ariſtander</hi> was by her means, often brought into her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; but being at length ſenſible that it was all to no effect, ſhe reflected with ſome indignation, to have her Labours defeated, and however took reſolution within her ſelf, not to ſee ſo fair an opportunity utterly loſt. She knew there wanted not Lovers that would think themſelves happy in ſuch Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and therefore caſt about to beſtow her Endeavours, where the Benefit might be received with gratitude. In the mean time, the Viſits that ſhe made and receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> were very frequent. She was ſo far from being paſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33136:50"/> of youthful Diverſions and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments of Mirth, that ſhe was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Life of the Company; and where-ever ſhe was preſent, triumpht over Melancholy, both in her ſelf and others. <hi>Nicerotis</hi> and <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> had always found a great agreeableneſs in each others Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and the perplexity of her Affairs, had often made it neceſſary. Yet as much as they delighted in retired Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on together, <hi>Doriska</hi> ſtill brought ſo much eaſineſs and good humour along with her, that her coming was ſeldom unwelcome; and if the Nicety of his Friendſhip could have diſpenſed with what was propoſed, it would have been extreamly to her Content; but finding ſtill that a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Correſpondence was the utmoſt of his Deſign, ſhe thought ſuch poor Advances un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a Patroneſs of her Politicks, and ſo giving him wholly over, looks out for a new Adventurer.</p>
               <p>And it ſo fell out at this time, that a young Spark that was her Kinſman, had entertained no ſmall Paſſion for <hi>Nicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and (having obſerved the intimacy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them) was encouraged to apply himſelf to his Kinſwoman for her Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. The Propoſal was readily enough embraced by her, who engaged in a ſhort
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33136:51"/> time to bring his Deſires to effect, or forfeit her Conduct in Affairs of Love for ever. The young Gentleman was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly tranſported with her Anſwer, and whatever Difficulties he might apprehend, he had good confidence in ſo skilful a Guide. She therefore immediately beſtirs her in his behalf, with ſo much Craft and good Management, that (as Circumſtances ſtood) ſhe would not have fail'd of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs with a Lady of more reſervedneſs than <hi>Nicerotis.</hi> The Buſineſs in ſhort was ſo well agreed amongſt them, that he is kindly received, and almoſt continually in private with her, <hi>Aristander</hi> in the mean time, appearing in publick, both as her Friend to her Husband, and her Protector. It muſt be imagined, that he ſoon found it very uneaſie for him, to be Patron to theſe Practices, yet was uncertain what courſe to take, being cordially a Friend to <hi>Nicerotis,</hi> and unwilling to do any thing that might prove prejudicial to her Reputation. But there appearing no like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood of Diſcountenance of this Intrigue, he could not longer bear to have his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection made a Property, and thereupon diſcovers the whole truth of the Matter to his Wife <hi>Eubea,</hi> informing her withal, that it was requiſite for her to break off
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33136:51"/> her Acquaintance with <hi>Nicerotis. Eubea</hi> was very difficult at firſt, to believe any thing to the Prejudice of her Friends Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, yet being at length convinc'd thereof, ſhe judged it altogether neceſſary to ceaſe from converſing with her. She made choice by way of Letter to acquaint her with her Reſolution, and that in the mildeſt Terms ſhe could expreſs her ſelf. <hi>Nicerotis</hi> however fell into all the Violence of Paſſion at the Peruſal, yet as ſhe wanted not tenderneſs of Temper and Art of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhe ſent her this Reply.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Am ſorry that our Converſation is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Letters, and that this is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be the laſt of that kind too. The Thoughts of loſing your Friendſhip for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſtrikes me with unſpeakable ſurprize, yet my happineſs in poſſeſſing it, was ſo great, that I might without Prophecy, long ſince have concluded it was not always to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed; but this is not the only ill Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I have received at Fortunes hands, and <hi>Eubea</hi> well knows, that it is not the firſt, though the greateſt Affliction of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Nicerotis.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33136:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eubea</hi> read over theſe Lines with Tears, and ſummoned all her good Nature in her Excuſe, and particularly reflected on the Relation ſhe had formerly given, of her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Diſappointment in her firſt Love, and imputed altogether to that Misfortune, any frailty that ſhe might afterwards fall into. <hi>Ariſtander</hi> in the mean time was no leſs afflicted, his Kindneſs for <hi>Nicerotis</hi> was ſo great, that it was as much as he could do to contain it within the Bounds of Friendſhip; he was not inſenſible of her Beauty, and he always thought the pleaſure he poſſeſt in her Converſation, a ſufficient Recompence for any Toil or Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in the Management of her Affairs. So that his Uneaſineſs and Melancholy for being deprived of her Company, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as great, as if he had indulged himſelf in all the freedom of a Lover, and perhaps the innocent manner of their converſing together (as it was more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd and generous) ſo it gave ſomething of delight and endearment beyond the groſſer ſenſe. He ſeemed wholly at a loſs within himſelf, and with many a Sigh viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Walks, that had ſo often been the pleaſant Scenes of their Diſcourſe. On the other ſide, the Diſcontent and Grief where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Nicerotis</hi> was poſſeſt, proved of longer
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33136:52"/> continuance than could be expected from a Perſon of her airy humour, and it was as much as all <hi>Doriska's</hi> Art and Gaity could do, to bring her to any tolerable Quiet.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
